解散监管机构并非我们的初衷
We have no intention of dismantling the regulatory agencies.
但实际上 我们整天被这些低效繁琐的规则所纠缠
However, we must come to grips with inefficient and burdensome regulations.
我们要裁撤那些毫无效益非必要的部门
We will eliminate those that are unproductive and unnecessary.
取消那些过时的规章制度 授予银行全新的职权
Tearing down these antiquated walls and granting banks significant new authority.
银行业迎来利好消息
In a victory for the banking industry,
国会通过了立法
Congress has approved legislation
准许商业银行和投资银行进行合并
which will allow commercial and investment banks
形成史上最大的 业务覆盖全球的金融机构
to merge and form institutions of unprecedented size and global reach.
大而不倒
我认为我们没有必要为了防范管制风险而去增加管制
I think it's very important for us not to introduce regulation for regulation's sake.
我一直坚信着美国梦
I do believe in the American dream.
而拥有自己的房产则是梦开始的地方
Owning a home is a part of that dream.
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hd.cnscg.com/==--
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
我们正采取措施 帮助数以万计的美国人拥有自己的房产
We are taking action to bring many thousands of Americans closer to owning a home.
这项计划不仅有利于全体公民
This project not only is good for the soul of the country,
同时也能带动国家经济的发展
it's good for the pocketbook of the country as well.
房地产市场已经近乎疯狂
The housing market has reached frantic proportions.
大家似乎都在忙着盖房子 然后进行买卖
It seems that everybody is building, buying or selling.
道琼斯和标普指数双双创出新高
The Dow and the S&P both breaking records.
高盛集团今年的利润飙升93%
Profits soared 93% at Goldman Sachs this year.
交易员中的佼佼者和银行从业人员收入预计将达到1000万
Hotshot traders and bankers can expect to take home 10, 25,
2500万 甚至是5000万
and in some cases, $50 million.
这一切好得近乎天方夜谭了
Things that are too good to be true, are.
当你看到其中的...
When you see something coming...
房地产业的泡沫...
The real estate bubble...
- 房地产泡沫  - 泡沫
- Housing bubble.  - Bubble.
切不可视而不见
don't put it off.
要立即采取行动
Take action immediately.
泡沫会逐渐缓解 还是只能等到破灭?
Will there be a soft landing, or will the bubble burst?
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hd.cnscg.com/==--
协调：潇妹纸
翻译：Flower一休 千欲 蓝岸 wendychen11 13711 Kim
校对：微微
最新消息 次贷市场开始分崩离析
The new story, the mortgage meltdown.
由于次贷危机的发生 今天上午的最新数字表明
This morning in the mortgage meltdown, new numbers showing
失去住所的美国人数又创新高
that a record number of Americans are losing their homes.
在过去几个月的时间里 美国有70多家从事次贷业务的公司纷纷倒闭
More than 70 mortgage companies have failed in the last few months in America,
而现在贝尔斯登 以及大银行等大型企业
and now the biggest of the big companies, the Bear Stearns, the big banks,
要开始承担这一后果了
are caught holding the bag.
贝尔斯登 这家国内排名第五的投资银行
The fifth largest investment bank in the country, Bear Stearns,
以每股2美金的股价出售给了摩根大通银行
is being sold for just $2 a share to JPMorgan.
这宗交易是在政府的协助下进行的 目的是为了保全
It's being assisted by the government, which is stepping in to guarantee
贝尔斯登帐下的300亿美金的不良房地产资产
some $30 billion in Bear's toxic real estate assets.
你一定能想象得出来 Hank Paulson被布什总统任命为财政部长的时候
You've got to imagine that Hank Paulson didn't think he signed up for this
不会想到有一天会去签署这样一份文件
when President Bush picked him to become Treasury Secretary.
现在Hank Paulson可能不得不取消一些撤销管制的规定
Hank Paulson may now have to undo some of the deregulation measures
而这些措施恰恰是在他主管高盛集团时与华尔街上的同行们一直努力倡导的
that he and his peers on Wall Street pushed through when he ran Goldman.
Hank Paulson财长今天上午对Matt Lauer说
Treasury Secretary Hank Paulson telling Matt Lauer this morning,
"我们已经克服了一切困难 我对我们的市场充满信心
"We're all over it. I've got great confidence in our markets.
它们是富有弹性和可塑性的"
They're resilient. They're flexible."
Ali 事实上贝尔斯登的收购事件只是掀开了冰山一角
Ali, the truth is that Bear Stearns is only a very small fraction of this story.
我们的经济很可能会大幅衰退
Our economy could face far worse than a recession.
受贝尔斯登倒闭的影响 雷曼兄弟忙于
In the wake of Bear's collapse, Lehman Brothers is scrambling
说服投资者相信 次贷危机不会对雷曼兄弟的资产造成太大影响
to reassure investors about the impact of the mortgage crisis on its own assets.
今天上午雷曼兄弟的保证人遭受了一系列的压力
Insurers of the firm under a great deal of pressure this morning.
Dick Fuld 在雷曼工作了39年
Dick Fuld, a 39-year veteran of Lehman
并且是华尔街上大型投资银行中任职最久的首席执行官
and the longest-running CEO of a major investment bank on Wall Street,
曾多次让公司在危机中起死回生
has pulled the firm back from the brink during other crises,
Richard Fuld 雷曼兄弟主席兼首席执行官
但是今天 我第一次听到了投资者们对他的领导能力的质疑声
but today, for the first time that I'm hearing it, investors are questioning his leadership.
- 混蛋  - 投资者们
- Motherfucker.  - One key question
对雷曼兄弟最关注的一个问题就是
investors have for Lehman Brothers,
"这家投资银行的盈利能力到底如何?"
"What's the true earnings power of this investment bank's business?"
Joe Gregory 雷曼兄弟总裁兼首席运营官
- 嘿  - 赶紧到我这儿来
- Hey.  - Get up here.
我们得去搬救兵了
We gotta start stacking sand bags.
你在说什么啊?
What are you talking about?
我们的股价暴跌了21% 从市价上看 我个人就损失了9000万
We're down 21%. On paper, I just lost $90 million, personally.
随着投资者不断抛售雷曼兄弟的股票
With investors pummeling Lehman shares,
今天上午最大的一个疑问就是
the big question this morning is,
"Fuld还有何退路?"
"What options does Fuld have?"
截至目前 他还没能够筹措到新的投资
So far, he has failed to raise new capital
而事实上他的竞争对手们已经拿到了
while virtually all of his rivals have already done so.
财政部长 高盛前董事会主席兼首席执行官
现在 对冲基金经理David Einhorn已经在公开质疑公布数字的准确性了
And now, hedge fund manager David Einhorn is publicly questioning the accuracy of the fund numbers
有什么好消息吗?
Anything good?
这是一只红尾鹰 今年头回看到
It's a red-tailed hawk, first one this year.
Dick Fuld在1号线上等着
Dick Fuld's on one.
提供可信的答案
to provide credible answers.
让我们来一起分析一下这些 呃
So let's go through a couple of those, uh,
被你称为差异的东西 因为...
what you call discrepancies, because...
- 上午的日子不好过吧?  - 我们有高收益
- Tough morning?  - We show top-quality earnings,
- 粉碎了所有之前的预测  - 没错
- we beat every prediction.  - Yeah.
这是做空者的行为 你也知道他们的一贯伎俩 先做空 然后弯曲事实
It's the damn short-sellers. You know the game, short and distort.
他们善于散布谣言 然后从中大赚一笔
They're rumormongers and they're making a killing.
你对于筹集资金有什么计划?
What are your plans for a capital raise?
我们想的比你更远 让我把话再讲得明白些
We're way ahead of you. Now, let me be clear,
我们不需要现金
we don't need the cash.
这是一种直觉
You know, it's about perception.
快说巴菲特
Buffett, Buffett.
我们正在考虑同沃伦・巴菲特进行接洽
We're thinking of reaching out to Warren Buffett.
很好
Great.
你和巴菲特有过交情 对吧?
You and Buffett go back, right?
帮帮我 给他打个电话
Do me a favor and call him.
告诉他雷曼兄弟有着很坚实的基础
Tell him Lehman is rock solid.
作为财政部长 我不能鼓动他去进行某一项的投资
As Treasury Secretary, I can't advocate for a specific investment.
Erin Callan 雷曼兄弟首席财务官
Hank 你想不想让我筹集到资金?
Hank, you want me to raise capital or not?
2008年5月24日 星期六
雷曼兄弟的规模要比贝尔斯登大得多
Lehman Brothers is a hell of a lot bigger than Bear Stearns.
市场开始恐慌了
The market is terrified.
我在高盛集团主政期间 从来没有想过要去
When I was running Goldman, I never even conceived
请求财长为我促成一笔交易
of asking the Treasury Secretary to cut a deal for me.
没错 但是对贝尔斯登的紧急援助造成了...
Yeah, but the Bear bailout created...
不要把它说成是紧急援助
Please don't call it a bailout.
好吧 对贝尔斯登的一揽子大规模收购援助政策
Okay, the very large Bear Stearns purchase assistance package
使公众产生了一种预期
created an expectation.
Fuld正期待您的直接介入
Fuld's counting on direct intervention from you.
巴菲特可以轻而易举地解决这个问题
Buffett's a simple solution.
Jim Wilkinson 财政部参谋长
我觉得您应该去给他打这个电话
I think you make the call.
以什么身份呢? 他的朋友? 以前为他提供服务的人? 还是以财长的身份?
As what? Warren's friend? His former banker? The Treasury Secretary?
不 还是让Fuld自己去打给他吧
No. Fuld's calling him.
希望他能介入进来 这样大家都能安心了
Hopefully he'll jump in and we can all relax.
安心? 我们刚刚处理了一家投资银行 这会儿又有另一家在苟延残喘
Relax? We just buried one investment bank, we got another one that's barely breathing.
这是一场关乎信心的博弈 如果人们对雷曼兄弟失去了信心
This is a confidence game. People lose faith in Lehman,
那后面的银行就会像多米诺骨牌一样成片地倒下
these banks are gonna drop like dominoes,
而我也无法为此再做出什么了
and I don't have the authority to do a thing about it.
已经晚了 一切都已经太晚了
We're late. We've been late on everything.
Neel Kashkari 部长助理 处理国际事务
Neel的团队正在研究这样灾难即将带来的后果
Neel's team is working on some kind of a disaster scenario.
我们把它称为"破杯"计划
We're calling it the "Break the Glass" plan,
当您走投无路的时候就可以要求国会执行这项计划
what to ask Congress for if your back's against the wall.
钱呗
Money.
就是向他们要钱呗
Is what you ask them for.
Michele Davis 部长助理 处理公共事务
问题在于 除非我们已经撞上了冰山 否则国会不会采取举措
The problem is, Congress won't move until we've already hit the iceberg,
而到那时 一切都已经太晚了
and at that point, it may be too late.
你的意思是说 我掌管着美国财政部
So you're saying, with the full weight of the United States Treasury behind me,
而我能做的就是去找巴菲特求助?
all I can do is call Warren Buffett?
嗨 巴菲特 我是Hank
Hi, Warren. It's Hank.
我知道你和Dick Fuld已经谈过了
I understand you've been talking to Dick Fuld.
华伦・巴菲特 世上最富有的人
Hank 你也知道我对那些投资银行的担忧
You know my misgivings, Hank, about investment banks.
他们一旦开始为自己进行交易时
As soon as they started trading for themselves,
那些风险经理就都失控了
the risk managers lost control.
我和所罗门兄弟公司有过一次不太愉快的合作经历
I had a very unpleasant time with Salomon Brothers.
你说得有道理
That's fair enough.
但我们都知道投资银行向来都是一个有利可图的行业
But we both know that investment banking is a profitable business.
我猜它大概已经为你赚了数十亿美金了吧?
I figure it made you a billion or so, huh?
我相信如果他们出价合理的话 你也不会袖手旁观吧
I gotta believe that if the price was right, you wouldn't just walk away.
在事实面前才算数 你觉得呢?
You know a good deal when you see one. What say you?
还是你自己来判断吧
I gotta leave that to your judgment.
大家的反应就好像我们是奸商一样
People act like we're crack dealers.
没人拿着枪去指向某人说
Nobody put a gun to anybody's head and said,
"嘿 猎人 买下这栋你偿还不起的房子吧 等你住进去以后
"Hey, nimrod, buy a house you can't afford. And you know what? While you're at it,
再用它申请信用额度 这件就可以再买一艘船了"
put a line of credit on that baby and buy yourself a boat."
巴菲特给你回复了吗?
You heard anything from Buffett?
他要求获得股价为40美金的优先股 分红为9%
He's asking for preferred shares at 40 with a dividend of 9%.
股价刚还在66块呢 搞什么鬼啊?
We were just at 66. What the fuck?
或许这只是游戏的序幕吧 Dick
Maybe it's just an opening gambit, Dick.
听上去更像是一种侮辱
Sounds more like a goddamn insult.
- 我来帮你弄吧 Dick  - 谢谢
- Let me get that, Dick.  - Thank you.
我们的股价已经跌到了36块
We're at 36 right now.
这几个月以来我们从未到过66快附近
We haven't been anywhere near 66 in months.
市场喜欢巴菲特
The markets like Buffett.
- 他的名字会在一夜之间推动股价上升  - 我才不在乎他是谁
- His name will push the price up overnight.  - I don't care who he is,
我不会用1年花费3亿6000万的代价去取悦他以谋求合作
I am not spending $360 million a year for the pleasure of doing business with him.
房地产市场会重新振作起来的
Real estate will come back.
韩国人有意介入
Koreans have been sniffing around.
这不好了 他们不会漫天要价
There you go. And they won't steal us blind.
这种场面以前我也经历过 首席执行官们开始恐慌 然后廉价卖掉自己的股票
I've seen this before. CEOs panic and they sell out cheap.
现在 整条华尔街都认为已经到了火烧眉毛的时候
Right now, the Street's running around with its hair on fire,
但暴风雨总会过去的
but the storm always passes.
我们要充满信心 然后 去参加高盛举办的午宴
We stand strong, and on the other side, we'll eat Goldman's lunch.
那我们该如何回复巴菲特呢?
So, what do we do about Buffett?
去他妈的巴菲特
Screw Warren Buffett.
每周早餐会议
- 他拒绝了?  - 雷曼兄弟的股价
- He passed?  - Lehman dropped
在今天上午已经跌到了28块半 他到底是怎么想的啊?
to 28 and a half this morning. What in the world is he thinking?
他根本没有思考 他是在妄想 他认为巴菲特的开价太高了
He's not thinking. He's delusional. He thought the ask was too high.
Ben Bernanke 联邦储蓄主席
他得去筹措资金啊
He's gotta raise cash.
我也是这么跟他说的
I told him that.
- 我找格林斯潘谈过了  - 真的吗?
- I spoke to Greenspan.  - Really?
他说住房市场供过于求 这就是问题所在
He says there's too much housing supply. That's the problem.
所以我们应该买下所有闲置房屋 不让它们流入市场
So we should buy up all the vacant houses and burn them.
Dick需要一个能认清现状的买家
Dick needs a buyer, someone with a grip on reality.
几个月前巴克莱银行曾表示过些许兴趣
Barclays expressed some interest a couple of months ago,
但我觉得现在的股价还没有降到他们的心理价位
but I don't think the price is low enough for them.
- 美国银行呢?  - 有这个可能
- Bank of America?  - Possible.
Dick之前也试探过他们
Dick's put out feelers there before.
不过我们得保持低调
We have to keep it quiet, though.
因为一旦有人获悉他们准备出售
'Cause if anyone hears that they're trying to sell
雷曼兄弟将瞬间完蛋
Lehman'll be dead within the hour.
2008年6月11日 雷曼兄弟高管紧急决策会议
在房地产业务上的投资正在毁掉整个公司
The real estate investments are killing the firm.
我们得公开承认我们犯了一些错误
We have to admit publically we've made some mistakes.
我们需要对高管层进行更替
We need to make a senior management change,
从而向市场表明我们的立场
signal to the market that we get it.
- 你们指的是谁?  - Joe Gregory
- Meaning what?  - Meaning Joe Gregory.
别扯淡了
Get the fuck out of here.
还轮不到你们来告诉我该如何来运营我的公司
You are not gonna tell me how to run my company.
Joe在这场危机中没有站在你这边 这是人所共知的
Joe hasn't had your back on risk, and everyone knows it.
Erin Callan也得走人 整条华尔街都知道她就是个笑话
Erin Callan's gotta go, too. As far as the Street's concerned, she's a joke.
Joe Gregory和我共事了30多年
Joe Gregory has been with me for 30 years.
我们只是遇到了暂时性的困难 你们就想让我把他撵走?
And you want me to kick him to the curb because we had a bad quarter?
这不是暂时性的困难
It's not just a bad quarter.
股价已经跌到23块了
Stock hit 23.
Skip McGee 雷曼兄弟投行部 全球区总裁
23块啊 公司大部分员工分到的股票都是在数年内无法进行买卖的
Twenty-three. Most of our guys are paid in stock they can't sell for years.
他们损失的是过去六个月里赚的净利润
They've lost most of their net worth over the last six months.
如果你不稳住股价 你的那些交易员们只能跑路了
You don't stabilize the price, your traders are gonna jump ship.
一群自私鬼
Selfish fucks.
Dick 不仅是银行家和交易员们 连客户都会抽走他们的资金
It's not just bankers and traders, Dick. Clients are pulling their money.
公司将遭遇到连锁反应
There's gonna be a run on this bank.
消息灵通人士对财经频道透露
Sources tell CNBC that both
雷曼兄弟的Erin Callan和Joseph Gregory已经离任
Erin Callan and Joseph Gregory are out at Lehman Brothers.
公司的主席Dick Fuld在一份声明中称
In a statement, the company's chairman, Dick Fuld, said
2008年8月4日
将由48岁的Bart McDade代替Gregory的位子
replacing Gregory with 48-year-old Bart McDade
Bart McDade 雷曼兄弟新总裁兼首席运营官
这是他所做过的最艰难的一个决定
has been one of the most difficult decisions he's had to make.
Dick 韩国人刚刚到达Sullivan
Dick, the Koreans just arrived at Sullivan.
我们一定要抓住这次机会
Let's go make this happen.
我觉得这会儿你最好就待在这里
My take is you'd be better off staying here for now.
我们要把你打造成为"幕后人士"
We need you to be our "missing man."
由我们去谈 尽最大努力去促成这笔交易
We'll go in and push the deal as far as we can,
最后再由你出面来达成这笔交易
and then we'll bring you in at the end to top it off.
好吧 听你的
All right, fine.
很好
Okay. Okay.
我们如期来到了纽约
We are committed to our presence in New York.
但我们需要知道确切的数字
But we need to know that the underlying numbers make sense.
我们也看到了事情的发展情况
We realize how things look.
但我们的股价只是被一些做空者暂时挫伤
But our stock is getting hammered by the shorts.
它的真实价值依旧没变
The value is still there.
我们刚刚开始谈 Min还是很兴奋的 但他们还没有给出具体的数字
We just started. Min's excited, but we haven't heard the terms.
你在哪儿?
Where are you?
我刚走出会议室来接你的电话啊
I just stepped out to take the call.
快回去 要有礼貌啊
Get back in there. Don't be rude.
好的
Okay.
我们只是将你们不感兴趣的那一部分资产
We simply take the assets you don't find appealing,
拆分成一个独立的公司
spin them off into a separate company.
- 你不必买下整家银行  - 抱歉
- You don't buy that bank.  - I'm very sorry.
你只需买下这家运营良好的银行就行了
You buy the good bank.
他们对房地产不感兴趣
Look, they don't like the real estate.
什么叫他们不感兴趣?
What do you mean, they don't like it?
Dick 我们终于有些进展了 暂时不要打扰我了
Dick, we're making real progress here, okay? Let me stay on it for now.
Min 你好
Min, how are you?
很高兴见到你
Great to see you.
希望没有打扰到你们
I don't want to interrupt.
Dick 你来得正是时候
Dick, great timing.
看起来双方对合同的大致框架都很满意
We seem to be in sync on the broad strokes of the deal.
我们可以回到意向书上来了吗?
Shall we get back to the letter of intent?
Min 我不得不告诉你 我觉得你正在犯一个大错
Min, I have to tell you, I think you're making a big mistake here.
房地产资产价值巨大
There's great value in the real estate assets.
要不通过仔细分析投资组合
How about we walk through the portfolio
我来向你展示这一点如何?
and I'll show you?
我们已经仔细看过了
We have looked at them.
有些地方你肯定没看懂
Then you must have looked at them in the wrong way.
我不想看你做出错误的决定
See, I just don't wanna see you leave money on the table.
或许我们应该休息一下
Perhaps we should take a break.
Min 非常抱歉
Min, I'm so sorry.
我们一直在真心实意地进行谈判 突然就这么回到原点了?
We have negotiated in good faith. Now all of a sudden we are going backward?
我们同意你给出的报价
We can work with you on the price.
这与报价无关
It is not about the price.
我说的是你们处理事情的方式
It is about the way you have conducted this.
非常感谢大家
I'd like to thank you, all of you,
但我觉得已经没有继续谈下去的基础了
but I don't think we have a structure that works.
什么 就这么结束了?
What, that's it?
你们就打算这么打道回府了?
You're just gonna pack up and go back to Korea?
- 你好  - Neel 我是Dick Fuld
- Hello?  - Neel, it's Dick Fuld.
听着 如果Hank想让我找到买家
Listen, you know, if Hank wants me to find a buyer,
你们得出面帮我一把啊
you guys need to step up and help.
韩国人刚刚退出交易了
The Koreans just walked out, okay?
我只是表达一下自己的观点
Look, I'm just speaking for myself here,
但我认为你应该做一些有利于公司的事情
but I think you need to do what's right for the firm.
什么叫有利于?
Do what's right?
这话是什么意思?
What is that supposed to mean?
如果股价继续下跌
If your stock price keeps sliding,
你也许会得到一个令人失望的报价
you may get an offer at a price that doesn't look all that compelling,
但为了公司的持续经营 你必须接受它
but you may have to take it just to keep the company intact.
你指什么样的买价?
What kind of price are you talking about?
可能会...
Could be...
我指 股价可能在个位数
I mean, it might be low single digits.
二月份 我们公司每股66美元
Last February, we were at 66 a share.
雷曼兄弟可不是贝尔斯登
Lehman Brothers is not Bear Stearns.
我们业绩很好的 房地产会复苏的
We've got a great business. Real estate's gonna come back.
我他妈不会把这公司送人的!
I am not fucking giving this company away!
在雷曼兄弟股价因其
While the real estate market has put
房地产业务而备受压力时
put Lehman Brothers shares under pressure,
房贷巨头房利美和房地美两公司传出报道说
mortgage giants Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac stocks
需要筹资750亿美元才能偿付其债务
are suddenly plummeting this morning, after reports the companies
此后 这两家公司的股价急剧下跌
may need to raise $75 billion just to remain solvent.
因为这两家公司几乎担保了
Because they guarantee such an enormous percentage
全国大部分的次级贷款
of the nation's mortgages,
有关人士预测政府将会介入
there is renewed speculation that the government
该事态中 收购两家公司
may have to step in and take them over,
政府介入的可能性也从奥巴马的竞选演讲中得到证实
a possibility Barack Obama has now raised on the campaign trail.
若房利美和房地美倒闭了
If Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac collapsed,
那么将会给整个金融界带来
then probably the financial system would receive such a body blow
灾难性的动荡
that it could be disastrous.
房地美下跌了8% 房利美下跌5%
Freddie just dropped another 8%. Fannie's down 5%.
Timothy Geithner 纽约联邦储备银行行长
下跌趋势迅猛 我们得采取措施了 立刻
There's no bottom here. We need to do something. Now.
我们正向国会提议
We're working on a proposal for Congress,
看能否批准我们向市场注资救市
see if we can get the authority to put some money in.
我本不想这么做的 但若情况特别糟糕的话...
I'd rather not go that way, but if we get there...
我想事态已经很糟糕了
I think we're already there.
- 你能要到多少?  - 一张空白支票
- How much are you gonna ask for?  - A blank check.
投资资金必须足以让我们挽救市场
It has to be enough of a statement to reassure the market.
得让市场觉得 我拥有决定性武器
They need to think I've got a bazooka in my pocket.
不是说我们真的会注资 只是如果我们得到了国会的许可
I'm not saying that we use it, but if we have the authority,
那么 所有疯狂抛售股票的人会逐渐冷静下来 重新参与
everyone who's dumping their shares will calm down, back off.
行 若你在国会 你也可以顺便提议资助那些投资银行 是吧?
Okay, if you're going to Congress, why don't we give to the banks, too?
因为雷曼兄弟眼看活不成了 美林也离破产不远了
'Cause Lehman's looking like shit and Merrill's not far behind.
光说服他们愿意接管房利美和房地美就够走运了
We'll be lucky to get them to move on Fannie and Freddie.
我们只能说试试看
We do what we can do.
北京奥运会开幕式 2008年8月8日
部长先生 部长夫人 请看这边
Secretary, Mrs. Paulson, over here.
请看这边 谢谢
Over here, please.
Paulson部长 请看这边 谢谢
Secretary Paulson, over here, please.
Paulson夫人 谢谢
Mrs. Paulson. Thank you.
Paulson夫人
Mr. Paulson.
Paulson部长 夫人 请看这边 谢谢
Mr. and Mrs. Paulson, this way, please.
- 我来抱着  - 带她先去一边
- I've got her.  - You should take her.
请看这边 Paulson部长 谢谢
Right over here, Secretary Paulson, please.
请笑一笑 谢谢
Big smile. Thank you.
这正是我需要的
That's just what I need.
新闻媒体拍到美国财政部长居然挥舞着中国国旗
Press photos of the Treasury Secretary waving the Chinese flag.
Paulson竟然是共产党员 你当时脸上的表情很精彩的
Paulson the Communist. The look on your face was priceless.
Hank 关于房利美和房地美 我有问题要问
Hank, I must ask you about Fannie and Freddie.
我们在"两房"公司投资了数十亿美元
We have hundreds of billions invested.
你和我保证过投资是安全的
You've assured us the investment is safe.
是的 绝对安全
And it is, absolutely.
可我们发现 近期损失了很大一笔数额
We're watching a great deal of our money disappear.
两个月内 股价竟然跌了60%
Share prices have dropped 60% in the last two months.
光到处宣扬你有决定性武器可以救市是不够的
Carrying your bazooka around has not helped matters.
国会给了你权利 也许是时候使用这项权利了
Congress gave you the power. Perhaps it is time to use it.
市场会稳定下来的 需要的只是时间而已
The market will stabilize. We just have to give it some time.
俄罗斯上个月和我们联系
There was an approach last month from Russia.
他们也持有大量房利美和房地美的的债券
They have considerable holdings in Fannie and Freddie as well.
俄罗斯建议我和他们合作 搞一次突击
They suggested we coordinate, and without warning,
向市场大量抛售房利美
dump hundreds of billions of Fannie
和房地美的债卷
and Freddie's bonds onto the market.
- 那市场就会...  - 一片混乱
- That would be...  - Chaos.
贵国发售过多的债卷
The amount of debt your country carries
是你们一处致命的弱点
is a terrible vulnerability.
- 但你们...  - 我们很客气地拒绝了
- But you...  - We declined, respectfully.
即使是在美国
Even in the US, it seems
你们政府和非国营企业
the relationship between the government
的关系似乎也是挺复杂的
and private industry isn't so simple.
他在威胁我们?
Was it a threat?
不 不是 只能算一个友情提示
No, no, it was a friendly reminder
提示我们 只要他们给莫斯科打一个电话
that with a single phone call to Moscow,
我们美国经济就会全面崩溃
they can take down the entire US economy.
从账面来看 房利美和房地美简直就是一团糟
The book says Fannie and Freddie are a nightmare.
负债缺口至少有数百亿美元
They are in the hole easily tens of billions of dollars.
过不了几周 他们就无法偿还债务了
Another few weeks, they're gonna start defaulting on their debts.
政府得介入干预此事了
We're gonna have to step in.
我不明白该怎么做
I don't see how we can avoid it.
看来武器不开一枪是震慑不住市场的
Turns out a bazooka's not that useful unless you fire it.
雷曼兄弟股价又跌了10%
Lehman's down another 10%.
你就不让我安心地咬一口面包 是吧?
You are not gonna let me get down a single bite, are you?
所以我早餐吃燕麦粥
This is why I have oatmeal.
Dick现在正满世界地乞求援助
Dick is trotting around the world with his hat in his hands,
但就是没人给他钱
no one will give him any money.
韩国老板放弃了他 墨西哥人叫他别管了
Korea walked out on him. Mexico told him to shove it.
没人对他公司感兴趣 所有能忽悠到的融资早就入股了
No one's interested. All the dumb money's already in.
那找美国银行如何? 他们还有兴趣吧?
What about B of A? Are they still in the mix?
巴克莱银行也开始蠢蠢欲动了
And Barclays is sniffing around again,
他们认为此时是买入的好时机
now that they think it's a fire sale.
- 这倒不错  - 鬼知道
- That's promising.  - I don't know.
那些英国佬光会说说 从未付诸行动(巴克莱银行是英国最大商业银行之一)
The British, they do a lot of talking. They never close.
- 美国银行是目前最好的收购者了  - 雷曼不能步贝尔斯登后尘
- B of A is still our best bet.  - This can't be another Bear.
不会的 他们会认购雷曼的全部股份
Absolutely not. They want Lehman, they buy it outright.
但他们需要我们经济上的帮助
But they may need a little hand-holding, though.
因为他们才收购了美国国家金融服务公司 所以口袋里有点紧
They just bought Countrywide. They're spread a little thin.
央行对美国银行资本充足率要求得暂时松一松
You may have to give them a break with the capital requirements.
你想让我允许美国银行提高他们的杠杆比率(偿还财务能力比率)
You want me to allow them to raise their leverage
这样他们就能收购另一家
so they can buy a bank that's about
因杠杆比率过高而即将破产的银行?
to fail because it was overleveraged?
你有更好意见?
You got a better idea?
突发新闻刚刚传来 财经频道刚刚收到消息
Breaking news just coming in. Sources telling CNBC
政府最近宣布接管
that the government has just taken
房利美和房地美公司
control of Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac.
然而在七月份 您可能会记起 Hank Paulson曾说过
Back in July, you remember, Hank Paulson said
他想让通过此举来介入
that he wanted the power to step in,
但他可能不会采取行动
but he probably wouldn't use it.
现在看来Paulson
It certainly sounds like Paulson
不得不用起他手里的武器了
just pulled the trigger on that bazooka.
虽然房利美和房地美公司正在进行国有化
Despite the move to nationalize Fannie and Freddie,
2008年9月11号 纽约市区
但股市仍然全盘处于下跌状态
the market is still in negative territory across the board.
投资者们现在正关注雷曼兄弟的命运
Investors now focusing their attention on Lehman Brothers,
尤其是有传言说 这家美国
amid fresh reports that the nation's
第四大投资银行
fourth-largest investment bank
正处于破产边缘
may be on the brink of bankruptcy.
嘿 Rodge
Rodge.
你好 Chris
Chris.
今天带钱来了 对吧?
Bring your money today, huh?
Chris Flowers 银行收购专家
别让Fuld再隐藏什么对公司不好的消息了
Make sure Fuld's not keeping any bad news out of the mix.
用Dick的话来说就是"大白于天下"
It's "open kimono," to quote Dick.
Rodgin Cohen 雷曼兄弟辩护律师
他让人讨厌
There's a revolting image.
你研究他们的数据了吗?
Did, uh, you get a look at the numbers?
房地产资产是个问题 他们对其定价300亿美元
The real estate's the issue. They got it marked at 30 billion.
估计高估了一半 别这么紧张
It's worth maybe half of that. Don't look so nervous.
你们只需要花买一个热狗的钱
You're about to get a Wall Street
就能买到这家华尔街的投资银行
bank for the price of a hot dog.
Greg Curl 美国银行策划部部长
我知道Paulson和Ken Lewis(美国银行首席执行官)
I know that Paulson told Ken Lewis
说过他不会介入此收购的
that he's not gonna pay for this.
若政府不出面接管一些不良资产的话
And I don't see how we can do it
我想我们还是无法收购雷曼的
unless the government takes some of the downside.
Paulson只是故作姿态
Paulson is posturing.
他会给你支票的 就像他曾让摩根大通
He'll write a check just like he did
收购贝尔斯登时一样
for Jamie Dimon on the Bear deal.
他必须这么做
He has to.
他可不能在总统竞选年度再损失一家大型投行了
He can't lose another major bank in an election year.
而且 那家伙在高盛的时候
Besides, the guy made, like, a half
最起码赚了五亿美元
a billion bucks at Goldman Sachs.
他让雷曼兄弟倒闭? 让高盛最强的竞争对手倒闭?
He lets Lehman die? Goldman's biggest competitor?
那会让人怀疑他还是高盛的人呢
Makes him look like he's still working for Goldman.
我估计他这会儿正在财政部写支票呢
He's just doing it out of a desk at Treasury.
甜甜圈在哪?
Where are the donuts?
就是如此 若你是他们这些金融企业的首席执行官
Exactly. If you're the CEO of one of these financial firms,
你早就注意到政府愿意支援你收购的话
you've already seen what the government was willing to do.
那你可以堂而皇之地说
Why wouldn't you play chicken with them and say,
"当然 我们愿意协助你们 可你得给我点好处吧?
"Sure, I'll help you out. But you gotta throw in a sweetener,
就像你援助别人收购时所作的"
just like you did for those guys"?
公众以为我们会资助Dick Fuld
They just assume I'm gonna bail out Dick Fuld,
以为我是那个为他们业绩不好擦屁股的人
like I'm the guy behind the elephant with the shovel.
公众认为雷曼兄弟这次被收购就像
They're all drawing a line from Bear
贝尔斯登 房利美和房地美一样
and Fannie and Freddie right to Lehman.
不会有纳税人再愿意支持资助另一家破产银行了
There's no way the taxpayers are gonna go for another bailout.
一揽子大规模收购援助政策
Very large purchase assistance package.
这次必须让他们自己去解决了
We need to come up with a private-sector solution,
让他们投行自己去弥补负债缺口
get the investment banks to bridge the gap.
可以 但除非他们确信您不会再
Okay, but that's never gonna work
支援该收购行动 否则行不通
unless they believe that you've drawn a line.
我知道您不喜欢向公众泄露消息 让我们和媒体交流
I know you don't like leaking, but let us reach out to the press.
好
Okay.
Flowers先生 您有电话
Mr. Flowers, there's a call for you.
是美国国际集团的Bob Willumstad 他坚持一定要与您通话
Bob Willumstad from AIG. He's very insistent.
Robert Willumstad 美国国际集团首席执行官
Flowers先生 我的人说你是这方面的专家
Mr. Flowers. My people tell me you're the man to talk to.
我们公司面临一个大问题
We've got a real problem here.
嗯? 什么样的问题?
Yeah? What kind of problem?
似乎我们的现金流就快断了
It looks very much like we are about to run out of cash.
美国国际集团?
AIG?
我们给您发了一份文件 是一份电子表格
We've sent over a document. It's a spreadsheet.
当然 这是一份机密文件 但会让您了解我们的困境的
It's confidential, of course, but it might give you some insight.
我正在处理雷曼兄弟的事情 美国银行要收购他们
I'm in the middle of Lehman. I'm working with B of A.
那您明天能过来一下吗?
Is there any way you could come over tomorrow?
我会研究下这张表 然后再说吧
I'll take a look at the numbers and we'll talk.
Flowers先生
Mr. Flowers.
谁去开下电视
Somebody put the TV on.
财经频道在说雷曼兄弟
CNBC's talking about Lehman.
一位熟悉Paulson的...
A person familiar with Paulson's...
一位了解财政部长Hank Paulson想法的人透露
Treasury Secretary Hank Paulson's thinking,
在目前这种经济环境下
and he is saying there will be no government money
政府不会资助美国银行收购雷曼兄弟
in the resolution of this situation.
他们说雷曼兄弟被收购和贝尔斯登的情况有两处不同
They're saying two things make the Lehman deal different.
雷曼兄弟收购是市场早已预料到的 并有半年时间
The market's been aware and had time to prepare
可以准备 第二点是...
for over six months. And the second is...
只是电视台在胡扯?
Is that just TV bullshit?
还是Paulson想给我们传递的信息?
Or is that Paulson sending us a message?
喂 Chris?
Chris?
什么? 不好意思
Yeah? Sorry.
"一位财政部部长的朋友"
What exactly does "a person familiar
这到底是什么意思?
with the Treasury Secretary" mean?
可能有很多的含义
That could mean a lot of things.
是你的某位员工胡言乱语吧?
Did one of your staffers do this?
一定是你十分钟前解雇了谁吧
Please tell me someone got fired 10 minutes ago.
那是我的意思
The leak came from me.
Hank 你那种公众宣言
Hank, a public statement like that
可能会引起很多想象不到的灾难
can have a lot of unintended consequences.
我们得提醒别的银行
We had to send a message to the other banks.
让他们自己解决了
They need to step up.
我的帽子里再也变不出兔子来了
I don't have another rabbit I can pull out of my hat.
Rodgin Cohen刚打电话给我
Rodgin Cohen just called me.
他说美国银行的收购团现在
The B of A team is sitting there
坐在那边在手机上玩打砖块
playing Brickbreaker on their phones.
他们不想收购了
They don't want this deal.
收购暂停是因为
The deal is hanging by a thread because
他们对雷曼调查得越仔细
the closer they get to Lehman,
就越觉得 这其实是一个废料排放场
the more it looks like a toxic waste dump.
所以我们得为他们收购做风险上的补偿
Which is why at the end of the day we may have to help them,
若您不作出那种公众宣言的话 这场收购本该是很顺利的...
which would be a lot easier if we didn't publicly state that...
我们不能 Tim! 那样做不合法!
We can't, Tim! Legally, we can't!
若要合法地做 那这场灾难我们也没办法阻止
Legally, we haven't figured out how yet.
我很担心
I am concerned
因为我们现在还有几种挽救措施 但我们正在
we are limiting our options at a time when we have very few,
浪费他们
if any, available.
我想让那些首席执行官聚集到一起 给他们一个周末的时间
I want all the CEOs in a room. We've got the weekend.
把他们关在美联储
We lock them in a room at the Fed
在他们自己解决雷曼兄弟这烂摊子之前 不放他们出来
and we don't let them out until they have a solution on Lehman.
你的燕麦粥快凉了
Your oatmeal's getting cold.
他们会明白事态严重性的 他们自己会掏钱的
They'll figure it out. They'll all throw in some money.
Tim强烈建议我们
Tim is advocating strongly that we
央行出面提供一些支援
reconsider some kind of Fed support.
他想让我们资助所有人
Tim wants us to pick up the tab on everyone.
我可不想做"破产救援大使"
I can't be Mr. Bailout.
而且雷曼兄弟的亏损是贝尔斯登的两倍
The Lehman hole is twice what Bear's was.
而且投资者正急着从中抽身出来
Investors are pulling their accounts.
你想长期借贷给他们吗?
You want to lend into a run?
那巴克莱银行呢? 他们仍想收购雷曼吗?
What about Barclays? Are they still interested?
他们在对待风险上比美国银行更加保守
They can't afford the risk any more than B of A can.
我相信你一定能够说服任何人掏出钱
I don't doubt your ability to talk anybody into submission,
但是这风险确实很大
but it is still a long shot.
而且雷曼兄弟很可能会破产
And there's a very real possibility that Lehman goes under.
这周将会有场收购谈判
There's a deal to be made here.
这场谈判一定会成功的
I'm gonna make the deal.
在收盘前不到一小时
With just a little more than an hour left until the market
雷曼兄弟的股价又猛跌了一把
closes, shares of Lehman Brothers have taken another tumble.
股价跌到新低 每股4美元都不到了
The stock is now trading at a new low, under $4 a share.
而且从卖方形势来看
And judging from the selling,
这种下跌趋势仍会继续
there doesn't appear to be a bottom in sight.
除了Blankfein(高盛首席执行官)说他有一场演讲 会尽量赶过来的
So, Blankfein has a speech he's trying to get out of,
其他的人都同意了
but the rest have confirmed.
- 告诉他必须来参加  - 好的
- Tell him it's not optional.  - Yeah.
Christopher Cox 美国证交会主席
下午好 主席 欢迎来参加该次会议
Good afternoon, Chairman. Thank you so much for joining us.
- 这架是谁的飞机?  - 呃 这是租来的
- Whose plane is this?  - Uh, that's a rental.
Hank自己掏钱的
Hank put it on his card.
先生 你认识Neel 这是Michele Davis负责公众事务
Sir, you know Neel and Michele Davis, Public Affairs.
嗨 很高兴见面
Hi. Pleasure.
- 这位是Dan Jester 我们团队的新人  - 你好
- This is Dan Jester, our new numbers guy.  - Hi.
是我劝他退休后继续出来工作的
I talked him into coming out of retirement.
- 什么? 退休?  - 我们以前在高盛是同事
- Excuse me? Retirement?  - He was with us at Goldman.
财政部还有没有员工不是从高盛过来的?
Got anybody at Treasury who wasn't at Goldman?
主席 有一点必须澄清一下
Chairman, just to be clear,
我们财政部和高盛之间没有任何利益冲突
there's no question of conflict of interest.
Hank在任职前就将高盛所有的股份抛售了
Hank sold all of his Goldman stock before he took office.
- 我什么也没暗示  - 不好意思
- I wasn't implying anything.  - Sorry.
我们对外面所传的"高盛政府"的谣言比较敏感
We're a little touchy about the whole "Government Sachs" thing.
我们走吧?
Shall we?
美国银行发现雷曼的不良资产越来越多
B of A keeps finding more toxic assets.
他们需要政府介入模仿之前摩根大通的收购
They want you to reconsider a Jamie deal.
他们会承担10亿元的损失
They'll split the first billion in losses,
剩余的40亿损失的由政府提供担保
but they want you on the hook for the next 40.
就像你对贝尔斯登收购做的一样
You did it for Bear.
Greg 我过会打给你
Greg, let me get back to you.
难道我得在我额头上纹个字才行吗?
What, do I have to tattoo it on my forehead?
我们不会对雷曼兄弟收购提供一分钱
We are not bailing out Lehman.
这是华尔街自己赌博失败
Wall Street has a gambling problem.
若老是让政府为他们擦屁股
If government keeps covering their losses,
他们永远也得不到教训
they never learn anything.
- 怎么了?  - 我不知道您是想继续
- What?  - I didn't know if you wanted
教导我道德危机
to keep lecturing me on moral hazard
还是想让我拒绝美国银行提议
or if I should just call B of A back.
我们只能让他们都坐在一起 进行讨论
We need to keep them at the table
直到这些企业找到自己的解决方法
until they come up with a private-sector solution.
告诉他们最好照我说的做
Tell them to stay with us.
- Alistair 你好啊  - 你好 Henry
- Alistair, hello.  - Hello, Henry.
请等一下
Hold on one second.
英国财政大臣打来的
Chancellor of the Exchequer.
我了解到巴克莱银行想收购雷曼兄弟
I understand Barclays is one of your potential buyers for Lehman.
但我国的银行最近的资金压力也很大
My banks are already under a great deal of stress.
我可不想承担过多义务
I don't want to become overextended.
雷曼兄弟虽然最近出了问题 但还是有价值的
Lehman is problematic, but there's value there.
我们会让他能够盈利的 继续保持合作吧
We will find a way to make it attractive. Just stay with us.
那再说吧
Talk soon then.
再见
Bye.
2008年9月18日 星期五
我们不会拒绝巴克莱银行 但最好还是由美国银行来收购
We'll keep Barclays in the mix, but B of A is still our best bet.
我们今晚会召集所有主要银行的首席执行官过来开会
We've got the CEOs of every major bank coming here tonight.
我们得明白地告诉他们 这是他们自己捅的篓子
We have to make it clear that this is their problem,
我们政府可以做顾问或是盟友
that we are their advisors and their allies,
但我们不是他们的保险箱
but we are not their safety net.
对这些人 我们还能指望什么呢?
What should we expect from these guys?
纽约 美联储
Jamie很聪明
Jamie is smart.
他买下贝尔斯登后 手头可运作的资金就不多了
He doesn't have as much cash to work with since he bought Bear.
Jamie Dimon 摩根大通主席兼首席执行官
Lloyd是巨星
Lloyd's a superstar.
高盛是华尔街上最精明的一家
Goldman's the smartest shop on the Block.
虽然我之前当过他老板 但那并不表示 他就会听我的了
And just because I used to be his boss, it doesn't mean he's gonna listen to me.
Lloyd Blackfein 高盛主席兼首席执行官
John Mack 他过去常常满楼层东奔西跑 大呼小叫
John Mack, he used to run around the floor screaming,
"水里有血啊! 我们杀啊!"
"There's blood in the water! Let's go kill someone!"
他是好战分子
He's a fighter.
John Mack 摩根士丹利主席兼首席执行官
Thain是我在高盛的副手 他很自私 是个实用主义者
Thain was my number two at Goldman. He's selfish. He's a pragmatist.
他知道 如果雷曼兄弟倒了 下一个就轮到美林证券了
He knows if Lehman goes, Merrill's next.
John Thain 美林证券主席兼首席执行官
Vikram Pandit刚入职花旗
Vikram Pandit is the new guy at Citigroup.
没人知道 是他在运作花旗 还是花旗在运作他
No one knows if he's running Citi or if Citi's running him.
Vikram Pandit 花旗集团首席执行官
感谢各位匆忙之中赶来这里
Thanks for coming down here on such short notice.
下周一早上 雷曼兄弟将无法偿付其债务
Monday morning, Lehman will no longer be able to honor its obligations.
有两家有意购买 美国银行和巴克莱银行
We have two potential buyers. B of A and Barclays.
但如果没有第三方融资 它们都无法完成收购
Neither will take the company unless someone else finances part of the deal.
政府不会进行干预
The government is not in a position to step in.
上一次是最后一次 这次就由你们完成了
I did the last one. You're gonna do this one.
Dick Fuld在哪儿?
Where's Dick Fuld?
Dick不适合再做决定了
Dick's in no condition to make any decisions.
我们将各位分成三组
We're breaking you into three groups.
第一组 评估雷曼兄弟的不良资产
The first one will try to value Lehman's toxic assets.
第二组 设计投资架构 让大家都可以投资雷曼
The second one will work on some sort of structure for you all to invest in Lehman.
第三组 制定熄灯计划
And the third one works on the lights-out plan.
如果雷曼兄弟申请破产 我们需要考虑
If Lehman files for bankruptcy, we need to figure out
如何遏制对各家的损害
how to contain the damage to the rest of you.
天呐
Christ.
我们早就预见到会出现这种状况
We've all seen this coming for miles.
我认为 雷曼兄弟即使破产 也不会给我们公司带来太大影响
I don't think a Lehman bankruptcy takes down our firms.
所以呢 我们就只能祝福雷曼了吗?
What, are we crossing our fingers?
这是要求我们挽救竞争对手 别表现得好像在帮我们一样
You're asking us to save a competitor. Let's not act like you're doing us a favor.
各位 各位 大家都是伟大的美国人
Gentlemen, gentlemen, you are great Americans
这是承担我们的爱国责任
undertaking a patriotic duty.
各位的努力将为自身赢得
Your travail will earn you the love
举国的爱戴和感激
and gratitude of your country.
我记得 Thomas Paine(激进民主主义者)曾经说过 "这些..."
I think it was Thomas Paine who said, "These are..."
雷曼兄弟是在座各家银行的合作伙伴
Lehman is a trading partner for every bank in this room.
它的破产将对大家都有很大冲击
Their failure will be a massive blow to all of you.
这就是重点
This is your problem.
我们可以好好说说 为何会到如此地步
We can all argue about how we got here.
放松管制 衍生品 Dick Fuld决策不利
Deregulation, derivatives, Dick Fuld made bad decisions.
我们都有责任 这是灾难性的动荡
We're all responsible. It's a catastrophic mess.
政府已经竭尽所能 现在全靠你们了
The government's done whatever it can do. It's on you now.
各位该解决问题 付出代价了
You need to fix it and you need to pay for it.
我就直说了
Let me be clear.
没出力的人 我们会记下的
We will remember anyone who is not helpful.
2008年9月13日 星期六
你注意到这其中的小规律了吗?
Do you notice a little pattern here?
不见棺材不掉泪
We don't deal with things until there's some kind of emergency on the table.
是啊 不到最后一刻 没人会去处理的
Yeah, we don't deal with things until Friday.
现在一只脚已经踏进去了
Some kind of a weekend thing.
我们什么时候才能
When were we gonna figure out
找到解决投资银行的破产问题的好方法?
exactly how to handle the failure of an investment bank?
周末搞定吧
Let's do it over a weekend.
我刚刚跟一位密切关注现状的专家谈过
I talked to a person who is monitoring the situation out there,
他说 业界人士都期望 他们能和Jamie Dimon一样 得到政府的自助
and the person said they all want the same deal Jamie Dimon got,
但预计期望会落空
and they're not going to get it.
提醒一句 Chris Flowers正在大厅
Just a heads up, Chris Flowers is in the lobby.
他是美国银行收购雷曼案的顾问
He's consulting for B of A on Lehman.
Hank之前将Flowers挤出了高盛
Hank pushed Flowers out of Goldman.
昨天我们还认为雷曼的不良资产仅300亿 今天就涨到了700亿
Yesterday, we thought Lehman was holding 30 billion in crap. Today it's 70.
700亿不良资产 这还只是随机抽样
$70 billion in assets that we're valuing with a dartboard.
没事 我们会解决这个问题
No, we're gonna work this out.
除非政府干预 不然我们就停手
Unless you step in, we're ending this.
别忘了Dick
Don't forget about Dick.
好了 Dick Fuld不停打来电话 不停要求我们提高价格
Yeah, Dick Fuld keeps calling, hammering us to raise the price.
抱歉
Excuse me.
700亿不良资产 还无担保?
70 fucking billion and no collateral?
如果雷曼兄弟本周末破产
If Lehman Brothers fails this weekend,
专家们毫不怀疑 下一个将是美林证券
there's little doubt amongst the people I speak to that Merrill Lynch will be next.
信心是非常脆弱的
Confidence is a very fragile thing.
在金融市场里 信心的流失速度非常快
And in our financial markets, it is eroding very quickly.
雷曼撑不下去了 我们就是下一个 必须立刻采取措施了
Lehman's not gonna make it. We're next. We need to do something right now.
只有美国银行能救我们了 我可以打个电话看看
B of A's the only one out there. I can put in a call.
- 虽然这样会毁了雷曼 不过...  - 雷曼是自食其果
- It screws Lehman, but...  - Lehman screwed themselves.
Paulson已经划定了底线 雷曼完了 打电话吧
Paulson has drawn a line in the sand. Lehman is dead. Make the call.
你们考虑一下收购美林的股份吧
We'd like you guys to look at taking a stake in Merrill,
有约10%的利润
something in the neighborhood of 10%.
我不知道能否拿到10%的利润
I don't know if I can generate any interest in 10%,
不过如果是收购整家公司的话
but if the whole company's in play,
我们肯定是愿意考虑一下的
I bet that's something that we'd consider.
我们和雷曼?
Us and Lehman?
这种规模的收购 我们只能完成一家
Deal this size, there's only room for one.
毫无疑问 风险很大 但是只要各位不中途退出
It is a lot of risk, no question, but if you stay in the game,
- 就都能找到各自的解决之道  - 当然了
- we all will find a private solution.  - Absolutely.
别被这些数字吓到了 我们会解决的 雷曼是值得收购的
Don't get scared by the numbers. We'll figure it out. Lehman is worth owning.
各位 有空吗?
Guys, you got a second?
我昨天去过了美国国际集团
I was at AIG yesterday.
下周三 他们将有至少50亿的缺口
Next Wednesday, they got a $5 billion hole, minimum.
我跟沃伦・巴菲特联系过了 他表示绝对不会帮忙
I called Warren Buffett. He wouldn't touch it with a stick.
我们会调查清楚
We're looking into it.
这是一家非常大的公司
It's a very big company.
谢了 Chris 感谢你所有的帮助
Thanks, Chris. I appreciate all your help.
他们根本不了解状况
They're not on top of it.
看看这个
Look at this.
这可能吗?
Is this even possible?
美国国际集团?
AIG?
该死的
Holy shit.
调查清楚
Get into this.
嘿 John
John.
你明白现在的状况吗?
Do you see what's happening here?
你想好怎么为自己打算了吗?
Are you watching out for yourself?
我不笨 我正在采取行动
I'm not thick. I'm working on something.
你想去找美国银行
You're talking to B of A.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
我知道 这样对雷曼不好 但是我必须先顾好美林
I know it's not good for Lehman, but I have to take care of Merrill.
把雷曼扔给我来操心
Let me worry about Lehman.
巴克莱还没有退出
Barclays is still in the game.
你去搞定吧
Just get it done.
美国银行将收购美林
B of A is gonna buy Merrill.
我们必须让巴克莱出手
We need to make Barclays work.
我记得你说过 英国佬只说不做的
I thought you said the British never close.
他们就在外面 似乎真的很想收购
They're here. They seem to really want it.
只要我们主动一点 他们就会收购的
If we hold their hands, they'll close.
Rodgin 怎么回事? Geithner不接电话 Paulson也不接电话
Rodgin, what the fuck? I can't get Geithner. I can't get Paulson.
连我的手下现在也不接电话了
I can't even get my own goddamn employees to pick up the phone.
Dick 大家都太忙了
There's a lot happening down here, Dick.
噢 该死
Oh, fuck.
给我听好 你去告诉Geithner
You know what? You tell Geithner,
他要是不帮我把这事解决了 下一个就轮到美林了
he doesn't pull my ass out of the fire, Merrill's gonna be next.
他知道
He knows that.
Dick 他刚告诉我 他们正在为美林寻找出路
Dick, he just told me they're working on a solution for Merrill.
那群混蛋要去帮美林?
Those cocksuckers are gonna bail out Merrill?
不 不是美联储
No, no, not the Fed.
没有私营买家了 只有美国银行和...
There's no private buyers. There's just B of A and...
他们想让美国银行收购美林?
They're gonna put B of A together with Merrill?
还有巴克莱银行 Hank觉得...
We still have Barclays. Hank feels that...
联邦政府竟然给我帮倒忙?
The federal government is snaking my deal?
我简直不敢相信!
I cannot fucking believe this shit!
美国银行和美林达成协议了?
B of A made a deal with Merrill?
对 雷曼的问题还是没解决
Yeah, Lehman's still our problem.
2008年9月14日
再来这么一次 我可受不了了
I don't think I can take another day of this.
你是刚下梅赛德斯 来到纽约美联储
You're getting out of a Mercedes to go to the New York Federal Reserve.
可不是奥马哈海滩的希金斯快艇
It's not a Higgins boat on Omaha Beach.
好了 好了 时间已经够长了
Okay, okay, we've been here a long time.
别废话了
Let's stop fucking around.
政府想让华尔街付账
Main Street wants Wall Street to pay.
他们觉得 我们就是有钱的笨蛋
They think we're overpaid assholes.
没有哪条政策规定 一定要参与紧急援助
There's no politician who's gonna sign off on a bailout.
那为什么不去资助那些赚钱的人呢?
Why would you bail out people whose sole job is to make money?
简单点说一下现在的状况吧
So, let's make this real simple.
Hank认为 他可以把雷曼好的资产出售给巴克莱银行
Hank thinks he can sell the good parts of Lehman to Barclays,
但这样就得有人把拖垮这家公司的抵押房产接手下来
but someone has to take the real estate crap that's weighing down the company.
谁都不知道这些不良资产的价值
Nobody knows how much this shit is worth,
但我们很清楚 一定得有人买下这批资产 以完成收购
but we know somebody has to buy it to make a deal.
我不喜欢这样 没人喜欢这样
I don't like it. Nobody likes it.
那就别抱怨了 去做吧
Let's just suck it up and do it.
有多少人可以投个10亿元 阻止雷曼的颓势?
How many of you can kick in a billion dollars to stop Lehman from going down?
我投 10亿
I'm in. One billion.
好
Okay.
高盛投10亿
Goldman's in for a billion.
John 你呢?
John?
喂?
Yeah?
是
Yes.
好
Yeah.
是
Yes.
成功了 巴克莱银行愿意购买
We did it. Barclays came through.
太棒了!
Too goddamn right!
巴克莱不愿意要不动产资产 但是其他银行同意收购这部分了
Barclays won't touch the real estate assets, but the other banks agreed to cover those.
通知董事会 把大家都喊来 我们有交易要谈了
Call the board. Get everybody here. We got a deal to make.
好的
Okay.
晚上9点 伦敦
找到他了吗?
Did you get him?
Geithner不回我电话
Geithner doesn't return my calls.
我们一个人都找不到
We can't get hold of any of those people.
今天之前 没有我们发话 他们是签不了协议的
At the end of the day, they can't sign the deal without our say-so.
对 但是他们知道吗?
Yes, but do they know that?
对
Yes.
Callum McCarthy爵士 英国银监会主席
嗯 一定 既然他屈尊来电 那就放他一马吧
Yes, by all means, now that he deigns to call, put him through.
Callum爵士 抱歉没能回电
Sir Callum, sorry I haven't gotten back to you.
我们在处理巴克莱银行收购雷曼的事宜
We're just sorting through this Barclays deal for Lehman.
身为巴克莱银行的监管方
As Barclays' regulator,
我们非常关注这桩计划中的交易
we have serious concerns about this proposed arrangement.
什么? 你是说你不同意这桩交易?
What? Are you saying you won't approve the deal?
就算我们同意这桩交易 事实上并非如此
Even if we were comfortable with the agreement, which we are not,
巴克莱银行也需要至少提前30天征得股东同意
Barclays would need at least 30 days for shareholder approval.
不 不 不 他不能 他不能这样做
No, no, no, no, no, no. He can't. He can't do this.
- 他们能阻止交易吗?  - 是的 当然可以了
- Can they stop the deal?  - Yeah, of course they can stop the deal.
不过就算他们阻止不了 光是耽搁一下 雷曼也完了
But even if they don't stop it, the delay will kill it.
立刻给英国财政大臣打电话
Let's call the Chancellor of the Exchequer right now.
巴克莱银行绝对不会接受任何不良资产
None of those assets would be part of Barclays.
是 但是如果英国金融服务管理局要...
Yes, but if the FSA were to...
我们需要稳定的局势
We need stability.
当然
Of course.
对英国金融系统而言 它也是 你们肯定发现了
must be to the British financial system. Surely you see that.
当然
Yeah.
晚安 好运
I wish you good night and good luck.
晚安
Good night to you, too.
"我们不会引入你们的癌症"
"We don't want to import your cancer."
各位
Those of you
不想帮助巴克莱收购案的人
who didn't want to assist the Barclays deal,
现在可以松一口气了
you can breathe a sigh of relief.
交易取消
The deal's not gonna happen.
- 嘿 我们筹到钱了  - 交易没了
- Hey, we have the money.  - Deal's dead.
巴克莱的监管方不愿签字
British regulator won't sign off.
你们可以施压啊
There must be some pressure you can exert.
相信我 我已经尽力了
Trust me, I've done everything I can.
英国佬
The British,
耍了我们
they grin-fucked us.
Paulson有10万雇员 Geithner有200名律师
Paulson's got 100,000 employees. Geithner has 200 lawyers.
该死的Chris Cox有3千手下
Frigging Chris Cox has 3,000 people.
这群混蛋就没一个人拿起话筒
Not a single one of those assholes could pick up a phone,
给英国佬打电话 趁他们还没在周末剥削完我们的资金前
call the British, find out if there was a deal to be made
看看能不能搞定这桩交易?
before they spend the weekend sweating us for cash?
有人失误了
Somebody dropped the ball.
他们不是失误
They didn't drop the ball.
是有意犯错 激怒高管
They dropped the ball, kicked the coach in the nuts
故意把事情搞得一团糟
and took a crap in the quarterback's mouth.
当然
Of course.
联邦政府会有所行动
The Fed will do something.
必须的
They have to.
我们要马上对外宣布 雷曼破产的消息
We've got to announce the Lehman bankruptcy now.
如果亚洲股市开盘 收购案还没敲定 大家都要做最坏的打算
If Asia opens and this isn't locked down, everyone's gonna assume the worst.
证券跌价会导致美国银行收购美林的失败
The sell-off will kill the Merrill-B of A deal.
- 谁去发布公告?  - 我想应该有美国证监会来
- Who's gonna make the announcement?  - I think it's gotta be SEC.
对
Yeah.
好
Okay.
那就决定了 什么时候开始行动?
Let's do it here. How soon can we set that up?
现在
Right away.
我们可以用主楼层 门厅那里
We could use the main floor, the entrance hall.
我后面还能有雕像? 很棒
With the statue behind me? Excellent.
雷曼真的同意申请破产了?
Did Lehman actually agree to file?
Chris 给雷曼打电话
Chris, call Lehman.
确保他们马上申请
Make sure they file right now.
一定
Absolutely.
美国国际集团是个大麻烦
AIG's a huge problem.
账目一团乱 不过我现在可以告诉你
The books are a mess. But from what I can tell,
世界上一半的银行和这群家伙有关联
half the banks in the world are in bed with these guys.
所有做过按揭抵押的银行
Everyone who had a piece-of-crap mortgage security
都在美国国际集团为其风险投过保 我是说所有
bought insurance on their risk from AIG, and I mean everyone.
他们怎么能让这种事发生?
How could they let this happen?
他们肯定是觉得 房地产市场不会崩塌 绝不会
They must have figured real estate would never go down, ever.
Hank 雷曼还没申请
Hank, Lehman still hasn't filed.
Cox必须要发布公告了 亚洲股市要开盘了
Cox has to make his announcement. Asia's opening.
他和他们谈过了吗?
Has he talked to them?
他根本还没打
He hasn't even called yet.
我们把巴克莱的事告诉了Fuld 我们说Cox会打电话给他
We told Fuld about Barclays. We said Cox was gonna call.
他就让所有股东坐在那里 不许接电话
He's got his entire board sitting there, no call.
Cox拒不开口
Cox is like a deer in the headlights.
混账!
Son of a bitch!
你是他们的监管方 马上给雷曼董事会打电话
You are their regulator. Call the Lehman board now.
Hank 现在的情况非常复杂...
Hank, it's a complicated situation where...
亚洲要开盘了
Asia's opening.
他们不公告 市场就完了
They don't announce, the market goes in the toilet.
我们必须考虑政府在其中扮演何种角色才比较恰当
We have to consider the appropriate role of government here.
我身为证监会主席 能否提议...
Can I, as Chairman of SEC, move forward and...
你们就像是不能出面的幕后人
You guys are like the gang that can't shoot straight.
这就是你们的工作
This is your job.
赶紧去打电话
Make the damn phone call.
Chris 我是Dick Fuld
Chris, this is Dick Fuld.
董事会成员正在开会 大家都到齐了 所有的股东和公司的法律顾问
The board is in session. Everyone is here. All the directors and the firm's counsel.
我们明白和巴克莱的谈判已经失败
We understand the Barclays deal has imploded.
我们在想你们有没有我们还没想到的解决方案
We were hoping you might have some option that we haven't thought of yet.
你知道 市场现在处于一团乱的状态
Um, the markets are in turmoil, as you know.
我相信 雷曼兄弟的破产
A Lehman bankruptcy will help
有助于消除不稳定性因素 起到稳定市场的作用
settle that uncertainty and, we believe, calm the market.
不管是联邦政府还是证监会都同意了
Both the Fed and SEC are in agreement about this.
让我...  不好意思 我来说说看看我是不是理解了
Let me... I'm sorry, let me see if I understand this.
你是想命令我们使雷曼兄弟破产吗?
Are you directing us to put Lehman into bankruptcy?
给我们几分钟
Give us a moment.
- 他们静音了  - 这是怎么回事?
- He's muted.  - What the hell was that?
让他们去申请破产
Tell them to file.
任何在本次会议上的发言会被作为公共记录
Everything said in that meeting is or will be public record.
我不能命令一家私人公司申请破产
I can't tell a private company to file for bankruptcy.
我没这权利的吧?
I don't have that power. Do I?
去做
Do it.
董事会需要做出一个决定 提出破产保护的申请
The decision to file for bankruptcy protection is one the board needs to make.
这并非政府的决定 但我们相信
It is not the government's decision. But we do believe
必须有人来解决问题
that the situation should be resolved.
所以你不是在命令我们申请?
So you're not directing us to file?
我要说的就这么多了 谢谢
I'm not saying anything more than I've just said. Thank you.
投票吧
Take the vote.
- Akers先生?  - 同意
- Mr. Akers?  - Yes.
Christopher先生?
Sir Christopher?
同意
Yes.
Admiral Evans呢?
Admiral Evans?
很遗憾 我同意
I'm sorry, but yes.
Chairman Fuld呢?
Chairman Fuld?
Dick呢?
Dick?
同意
Yes.
- Hernandez先生?  - 同意
- Mr. Hernandez?  - Yes.
- Ainslie先生?  - 同意
- Mr. Ainslie?  - Yes.
- Berlind先生?  - 同意
- Mr. Berlind?  - Yes.
- Cruikshank先生?  - 同意
- Mr. Cruikshank?  - Yes.
- Kaufman博士?  - 同意
- Dr. Kaufman?  - Yes.
- Macomber先生?  - 同意
- Mr. Macomber?  - Yes.
是P吗?
P?
- 雷曼完蛋了  - 哦 亲爱的
- Lehman's gone.  - Oh, honey.
我本该料到英国那边会出问题的
I should have known the British were gonna be a problem.
两天前我和他们谈过 那时我应该察觉出言下之意的
I spoke to them two days ago. I should have read between the lines.
你不能独自承受一切 这件事涉及了太多人
You can't take all this on. There's a lot of other people involved.
是我的问题 因为我是财政部长
It's on me. I'm Treasury Secretary
在我的监管下 我国第四大投资银行
and the fourth-largest investment bank in the country
倒闭了
failed on my watch.
我是说...
I mean...
我不知道将来会发生什么
I don't know what's gonna happen.
我也想你
Miss you, too.
2008年9月15日 周一  早上6:30
哟 出租车!
Yo, taxi!
亚洲股市大幅下跌收市
专家称:"Paulson终于让华尔街变得一文不值"
Jim 我现在在市中心
Jim, I'm in midtown.
电子指示器在...
The ticker is...
我看到的究竟是什么?
What the hell am I looking at?
Hank 没事
Hank, it's good.
"财政部和联邦储备局
"It is oddly reassuring
放弃雷曼兄弟的决定
"that the Treasury Department and the Federal Reserve
意想不到地让人感到舒心"
let Lehman Brothers fail."
好的 这条 这条
Okay, here it is. Here it is.
"政府的介入会被解读成
"Government intervention would have been seen
全球金融体系正处于极度动荡中
"as a sign of extreme peril in the global financial system
或是联邦管理当局的监管不力的标志
"or extreme weakness on the part of federal regulators."
该死的纽约时报
The New York fucking Times.
是啊 不仅是他们 每个人都这么说
Yeah, and it's not just them. It's everybody.
谢谢 议员 很感激你
Thank you, Senator. I appreciate it.
议会很喜欢
Congress is liking it.
我倒是不太确定他们是不是真这么高兴
I'm not sure they should be so happy about this,
不过他们觉得我们让雷曼退出是对的
but they like that we let Lehman go.
你态度强硬 你果敢 在这种时候 人们需要的就是这种态度
You stood strong. You've got brass balls. It's what people need at a time like this.
市场反应怎么样?
What is the market doing?
欧洲股指只出现小幅下跌 道琼斯指数也小幅下探了3%
Europe's only down a little. Dow Jones futures only off 3 %.
那你就得在新闻发布会上强调这点
So you need to build on this at the press conference.
你要告诉大家我们已经为雷曼兄弟做了我们能做的一切
The story is we did everything we could for Lehman.
- 我们的确做了  - 但是放弃的理由是...
- We did.  - And the takeaway is...
没有援助资金了
No more bailouts.
部长先生
Mr. Secretary.
我们应该如何解读发生在雷曼兄弟身上的事件?
How should we read what happened with Lehman?
解读成我认为维护市场的稳定和金融系统的有序
Read it as I think it's important to maintain the stability
是至关重要的
and orderliness of our financial system,
还有 呃 就是
and, um, the
我非常重视道德风险
moral hazard is something I don't take lightly.
- Paulson先生  - 部长 先生
- Mr. Paulson.  - Mr. Secretary, sir.
你认为现在的银行体系是否健全?
How do you see the health of the banking system today?
当今市场的运行
The way the markets are performing today,
是对于验证在极端情况下
it's a testament to how the financial industry has come together
整个金融行业是否能同心协力渡过难关的考验
in an extraordinary set of circumstances.
美国民众应该对金融系统的稳健和韧性
The American people can remain confident in the soundness and the resilience
持乐观态度 谢谢各位
of the financial system. Thank you all.
- 部长大人  - Paulson先生
- Mr. Secretary.  - Mr. Paulson.
怎么了?
What?
道琼斯大幅下挫 已经下跌了400点了
Dow is falling off a cliff. Four hundred points already.
整个信贷市场也处于冻结状态
And the credit markets are frozen.
高盛和摩根斯坦利收到大量撤资申请
Goldman and Morgan Stanley are getting slammed by withdrawals.
雷曼事件正在危及他们
The Lehman thing's killing them.
我得和总统谈谈我们该如何控制损失
I should talk to the President about how we'll contain the damage.
在你找总统谈话之前
Before you speak to the President,
我们还有个麻烦需要解决
we've got another problem.
是美国国际集团
AIG.
Geithner先生正在同美国国际集团探讨由企业主导的解决方案
Mr. Geithner is working with AIG on a private-sector solution
部长正非常谨慎地跟进他们的进展
and the Secretary is monitoring their progress very carefully.
他与国会领导者们也保持密切联系...
He's in close contact with the Congressional leadership, most...
白宫希望我们对美国国际集团的情况做简要汇报
White House wants a briefing on AIG.
你知道的比我们多 我们有的信息 你也有
You're more informed about that than we are. We've got the same information you do.
不 我们并不认为雷曼兄弟破产
No, we don't believe that Lehman's bankruptcy
足以整垮整个华尔街
is taking down all of Wall Street.
好吧 那你怎么解释...
Okay, but how do you explain...
美国国际集团的情况恶化的原因在于...
The AIG situation may have been, you know, exacerbated by the...
还有Barney Frank的办公室
And Barney Frank's office.
- 你好  - 突然发生?
- Yeah.  - A surprise?
不 美国国际集团已经挣扎了...
No, AIG has been struggling...
你们这帮人怎么没在6个月前阻止他们?
Why didn't you guys head off this situation six months ago?
因为我们没有魔杖 Doug
Because the requisite magic wand wasn't available, Doug.
如果我们找到了 我们会在第一时间通知你
But if we do find one, you will be among the very first to know.
Blankfei在四号线 紧急
Blankfein on four, urgent.
我得走了
I have to go.
嗨 Lloyd
Hey, Lloyd.
这该死的英国破产管理人
The goddamn British bankruptcy administrator
把所有雷曼客户的资产都冻结了
froze all of Lehman's customer accounts.
在你下决定之前你没有和他们协商好吗?
You didn't square this with the British before you did it?
Geithner 5号线
Geithner on five.
人们陷入了恐慌 他们拿不到钱
People are freaking out. They can't get their money.
不是投资者们 是客户们
Not investors, clients.
如果消费者觉得他们的钱放在雷曼那儿不安全
If customers think their money wasn't safe with Lehman,
他们也不会相信我们
they're not gonna trust us either.
没人愿意和我们做生意
No one will do business with us.
你得等我一下
You're gonna have to hang on.
Tim啊
Tim.
Dan和穆迪投资评级机构通话了 他们今晚要下调对美国国际集团的评级
Dan spoke to Moody's. They're downgrading AIG tonight.
虽说这事儿迟早会发生 但雷曼事件加速了下调的进程
Would have happened anyway, but Lehman put the whole thing into hyperdrive.
会降到哪一级?
How far down are they?
法国财政部长 6号线
French Finance Minister on six.
他们不知道
They don't know.
我们在努力挽救
We're working on it.
Christine啊
Christine.
你怎么能让这事情发生在雷曼身上?
How could you let this happen with Lehman?
Christine Lagarde 法国财政部长
你到底怎么想的?
What on earth were you thinking?
我们已做了我们该做的一切 Christine
We did everything we could, Christine.
你默许了雷曼破产 Hank 这大错特错
You allowed it to fail, Hank. It was a horrifying mistake.
这会给整个欧洲带来灾难性的结果
It is having catastrophic consequences all over Europe.
美国国际集团的情况会变得更糟
And AIG would be even worse.
整个欧洲银行都与美国国际集团往来密切
The European banks have tremendous exposure to AIG.
我们希望从你这儿得到保证 你不会让它像雷曼一样破产
We need assurance you will not fail to act, as you did with Lehman.
这不仅仅是美国的问题
It is not just an American problem.
非常感谢...
Thank you so much for...
是John Mack
John Mack.
- John  - John 一号线
- John.  - John, one.
雷曼的破产正连累着我们
The fallout from Lehman is killing us.
做空者都在抛售我们的股票 我们已经跌了10%
The short-sellers are all over us. We're down 10 % already.
你们不知道外面情况有多糟
You guys have no idea what's going on out here.
你的收入怎么样?
How are your earnings?
很好 我们准备周五公布消息
Strong. We're gonna announce Friday.
现在就公布
Announce now.
好了 Lloyd 不好意思
Okay, Lloyd, sorry.
Hank 如果储户们发现他们不能从雷曼的账户上取款
Hank, if depositors see they can't get their assets out of Lehman,
接下来就会有大批人从各投资银行撤资
the next step is gonna be a massive pullout from all the investment banks.
Jeff Immelt 通用电气
Jeff Immelt from GE.
天呐 Immelt为什么打电话给你?
Jesus, what's Immelt calling you for?
我得挂了 Jeff
I have to go. Jeff.
你得知道现在时态变成什么样子
You gotta know what's going on out here.
Jeffery Immelt 世界最大公司 通用电气 主席兼首席执行官
我们每天的营运现金流出现了问题
We're having trouble funding our day-to-day operations.
我们的财务部影响其他各个部门
Our finance division is infecting the rest of our business.
通用电气?
General Electric?
这件事情波及的不仅仅是华尔街的公司
This thing is spreading way past Wall Street.
我明白没有人想去碰次级贷款
I get that nobody wants to touch mortgages,
但我们要制造飞机 引擎 灯泡
but we're making planes and engines, light bulbs.
我们是家健康的企业
We're a healthy company.
如果我们不能有充足的日常营运资金来运营公司
If we can't finance our day-to-day operations,
那我们在美国所有的业务都有可能无法运作
every business in America's gonna be shutting down.
- 美国国际集团股价多少?  - 收盘价2美元
- Where's AIG?  - It closed at $2.
Tim觉得我们得采取有力行动 Ben和我都同意了
Tim thinks we need to do something big. Ben agrees, and so do I.
我们能做什么? 美国国际集团又不是银行
What can we do? AIG's not even a bank.
联邦政府会在非常紧急时期借钱给非银行机构
The Fed can lend to non-banks under unusual and exigent circumstances.
我们考虑接手80%美国国际集团的股份
We're thinking of taking over 80% of the company.
Hank 我们不能这么做
Hank, we can't.
今天上午我们还向全体公民普及了道德风险观念
This morning we were lecturing the entire country on moral hazard.
美国国际集团有抵押品 他们有资产
AIG has collateral. They have assets.
雷曼兄弟没有 我们不能借钱给一个无底洞
Lehman didn't. We couldn't lend into a hole.
两者情况不同
It's not the same story.
没人会在乎这些
Nobody's gonna care.
这又是一桩没有监管的注资行为
It's another bailout with no legislation.
国会会大做文章 整个国家也会抓狂的
The Hill's gonna go crazy. The country's gonna go crazy.
我们早上乘坐的班机是从美国国际集团租赁的
The plane that we flew in on this morning, leased from AIG.
在市中心的建设 是美国国际集团承接的
Construction downtown, AIG.
寿险 8100万份保单 账面价值1.9兆亿元
Life insurance, 81 million policies with a face value of 1.9 trillion,
上百亿的教师退休金 美国国际集团的资产到处都是
billions of dollars in teachers' pensions, it's everywhere.
你想要大而不倒? 就是这个了
You want too big to fail? Here it is.
你有更好的主意吗? 我可是听着呢
You got a better idea? The suggestion box is wide open.
我也知道现在说这个不太恰当
I hate to do this right now,
但我得明天一大早得召开新闻发布会
but I'm gonna have to have a press call first thing,
但我真不知道该对他们说什么
and I really don't know what I'm gonna tell them.
告诉他们雷曼拖累了美国国际集团 同时兑现债务抵押债券
Tell them Lehman exacerbated AIG. The simultaneous payouts of CDOs
和信用违约掉期几乎要压垮...
and credit default swaps put catastrophic pressure on...
再往前追述一点
Go back further.
全球的投资的资金池...
The global pool of investment capital...
她得用英文来发布 从房地产业主开始说起
She has to do this in English. Start with the homeowners.
好吧 好吧 你该这么解释
Okay, okay, here's how you explain it.
华尔街开始将房产抵押贷款捆绑 形成住房抵押贷款证券
Wall Street started bundling home loans together, mortgage-backed securities,
再分成一份一份卖给投资者
and selling slices of those bundles to investors.
他们借此谋取暴利
And they were making big money,
于是他们就开始催促放贷者 说道
so they started pushing the lenders, saying,
"快点 我们需要更多的贷款"
"Come on, we need more loans."
放贷者已经将把钱放给信用等级高的借款人
The lenders had already given loans to borrowers with good credit,
于是他们退而求其次 降低标准
so they go bottom-feeding. They lower their criteria.
以前你需要有620积分的信用评分 加上20%的首付
Before, you needed a credit score of 620 and a down payment of 20%.
现在 500就可以了 零首付
Now, they'll settle for 500, no money down.
至于买方 走在大街上的普通人
And the buyer, the regular guy on the street,
以为专家们知道他们在干什么
assumes that the experts know what they're doing.
他自言自语道 "如果银行愿意借我钱
He's saying to himself, "If the bank's willing to loan me money,
"那我肯定还得起"
"I must be able to afford it."
所以他开始实现自己的美国梦
So he reaches for the American dream.
他买下了房子
He buys that house.
银行知道债券挂钩垃圾贷款是非常危险的
The banks knew securities based on shitbag mortgages were risky.
你得强调 "垃圾"这个词
You'll work on "shitbag."
为了控制负面影响 银行会开始购买一种保险
So to control their downside, the banks started buying a kind of insurance.
如果抵押贷款违约 保险公司买单
If mortgages default, insurance company pays,
违约掉期
default swap.
银行为他们的潜在损失投保 使报表中不会出现风险
The banks insure their potential losses to move the risk off their books
这样他们可以进行更多的投资 赚更多的钱
so they can invest more, make more money.
如果很多公司投保
And while a lot of companies insured this stuff,
那么就有一家公司蠢得要承担难以置信的风险
one was dumb enough to take on an almost unbelievable amount of risk.
- 美国国际集团  - 你要强调"蠢"
- AIG.  - And you'll work on "dumb."
那如果他们问我为什么他们会这么做呢?
And when they ask me why they did that?
- 手续费  - 上亿的手续费
- Fees.  - Hundreds of millions in fees.
美国国际集团估计房地产市场会继续走高
AIG figured the housing market would just keep going up,
可是意外发生了
but then the unexpected happens.
房价下跌
Housing prices go down.
这穷光蛋买了他的梦想之屋
The poor bastard who bought his dream house,
这恼人的抵押贷款利率不停上升
the teaser rate on his mortgage runs out.
他的还款额上升 他违约了
His payments go up. He defaults.
次级抵押证券出了问题 美国国际集团必须偿还掉期
Mortgage-backed securities tank. AIG has to pay off the swaps,
全球 同一时间 所有的保单违约了
all of them, all over the world, at the same time.
美国国际集团付不起了 入不敷出
AIG can't pay. AIG goes under.
每一家他们承保的银行都在同一天要求兑现保费
Every bank they insure books massive losses on the same day.
他们都入不敷出了
And then they all go under.
都倒闭了
It all comes down.
整个金融系统?
The whole financial system?
那我该怎么说 如果他们问我为什么这件事情没有得到妥善监管?
And what do I say when they ask me why it wasn't regulated?
没人想去监管
No one wanted to.
经济形势表现得太好了
We were making too much money.
你得强调 "经济形势表现得太好了"
You'll work on "We were making too much money."
喂 Hank 呃...
Hey, Hank. Um...
这些很温和 不过很有效
These are really mild, but they work.
我知道你信基督教科学派 不吃药(该派认为物质是虚幻的 疾病只能靠调整精神来治疗)
I know the whole Christian Scientist thing, that you don't take medicine.
不过你需要睡眠
But you need to sleep.
- Jim...  - Hank 不仅仅是为了你自己 好吗?
- Jim...  - Hank, not just for your own sake. Okay?
你看起来不太好
You don't look so good.
就在几分钟前 CNN得到确切消息 美联储正在协调
Just minutes ago, CNN has confirmed that the Federal Reserve is negotiating
拯救保险巨头美国国际集团
to rescue insurance giant AIG.
协调计划包括一份850亿美金的临时贷款
The negotiations could include an $85 billion temporary loan
用以延缓美国国际集团面临的倒闭
to stave off AIG's imminent collapse.
朋友们 这可是个爆炸新闻
This is a blockbuster, folks.
差不多昨天的这时候 很多在华尔街的人
About this time last night, many on Wall Street
担心今天会是一团乱
were fearing total disaster today.
于是 联邦政府又一次注资拯救另一家华尔街巨头
So, another federal bailout of another Wall Street giant.
还有 我们提到的 是一起重大的 重大的金融消息
Again, as we mentioned, big, big financial news.
并且这条消息影响到每一个买过401k养老保险计划的人
And this affects almost everyone out there who has a 401k.
这条消息在股市收市的三个半小时后发布出来...
The news comes about three and a half hours after the stock exchange closed on...
哦上帝啊
Motherfucker.
我们现在马上把时间交给Ali Velshi来看看这次危机的底线在哪里 Ali
We wanna go straight right now to Ali Velshi to kind of give us a bottom line on this, Ali.
然后我们来看看这次危机是不是会持续下去...
And then we're gonna get a lot more in depth...
美国国际集团得到了收于850亿的救援...
AIG securing an 85...
信贷市场的资金流动依旧很少
The credit markets are still frozen solid.
如果我们继续想这些公司注资
We keep dumping money into these companies
那么市场会慢慢稳定下来
so the markets will stabilize,
除此之外没别的办法了
and nothing helps.
我们不能一直这样
We can't keep doing this.
我们无条件的救了贝尔斯登 又无条件的救了美国国际集团
We rescued Bear with no legislation, AIG with no legislation.
人们会认为房利美和房地美在诱售
People think Fannie and Freddie was a bait-and-switch.
你以为我愿意这样做吗 但是他们的状况都很特殊
I don't like it any more than you do, but they were exceptional situations.
现在的情况要求
This situation demands an endgame
那些公司不能再依靠联邦政府的协助
that does not rely on unilateral action from the Fed.
这才是民主
This is a democracy.
我们不能垂帘听政在幕后操纵
We cannot be men behind the curtain pulling the strings.
我们需要找到一个完善的解决方法来修复整个金融体系
We need some kind of an overall solution that heals the entire system.
并且是通过合法的方式进行
And it has to be legitimate.
我们一再推迟了向国会汇报这些事情
We've been putting off going to Congress.
离大选只有两个月了
It's two months before an election.
选民们不可能投票给一个使得整个银行系统崩溃的政府
They can't vote yes to a massive bailout of the entire banking system.
- 选民们不可能再选择我们  - Hank...
- They'd never get reelected.  - Hank...
我们去国会说清楚我们已经对现在的局势
We go to Congress, publically state we don't have the firepower
无能为力了 但是他们说不行
to control this anymore, and then they say no,
这种场景真是一场噩梦
that is really the nightmare scenario.
噩梦场景已经出现了 我的朋友
The nightmare scenario's already here, my friend.
而且我们深陷其中
We're in it.
P你还好吗
P.
你不能把所有事情都自己扛下来
You can't put this all on your own shoulders.
我们已经别无选择了
We're running out of options.
那么你就继续尝试别的方法 这才是你该做的
Then you just keep trying. That's what you do.
最后肯定会有办法解决的
Eventually something's gonna work.
我都不知道 是不是这样的了
I'm not sure that that is true anymore.
但是这世界上没有一家银行是有足够的钱去应对
There's not a bank in the world that has enough money in its vault
储户的提款要求 银行都是建立在信用基础上的
to pay its depositors. It's all built on trust.
而且 Wendy 我们已经岌岌可危了
And, Wendy, we are so very close.
摩根斯坦利 高盛已经在悬崖边缘
Morgan Stanley, Goldman are an inch away.
如果别的银行不再信任他们 如果他们停止了银行间的拆借
If the other banks stop trusting them, if they pull back on interbank lending,
他们会立刻破产
it's over in a matter of hours.
而且一旦破产开始了就不会停下来 会有连锁反应
And from there it goes too fast to stop, a run,
而且到时候破产的就不仅仅是银行了 整个金融系统都会崩塌
and not just on one bank, I mean on the whole system.
然后大众就会问 "我的钱安全吗?"
And average people wondering, "Is my money safe?"
他们开始提现
They start pulling their cash.
再然后 银行门口就会排起长队 ATM机就会被挤爆
And after that, lines outside the banks, smashed ATMs.
再过几个星期
A couple of weeks,
银行里就没有钱可以提了
there's no milk in the store.
这已经是本周第二次
For the second time this week,
华尔街出现了大量的抛售
there was a massive sell-off on Wall Street,
道琼斯工业指数暴跌超过450点
the Dow Jones Industrial's freefalling some 450 points
因为消息称纳税人的资金用来救援美国国际集团保险公司
on news of a taxpayer-funded bailout of the AIG insurance company.
五大投行中三家已经倒闭了
Three of the five investment banks are gone.
全国最大的抵押贷款机构也倒闭了
The country's biggest mortgage lender is gone.
房利美 房地美也已经收归国有
Fannie Mae, Freddie Mac, brought under government control.
金融系统现在算是保住了 但是能维持多久?
The financial system is holding right now, but for how long?
全部人力 全部资源都被完全利用
All the king's horses and all the king's men
一定保持金融体系的顺利运行
are being brought to bear to keep this thing together.
- 嗨 Tim  - 我在华尔街 Hank
- Hi, Tim.  - I'm on the Street, Hank,
人们正要赶着去上班
and people are just going about their business.
他们完全不知道这里的一切都将化为乌有
They have no idea the whole thing is about to fall down.
我们不得不向国会报告了 我们已经别无选择
We're gonna have to go to Congress. We don't have a choice anymore.
好吧
Okay.
你觉得还要多久他们会做出决定?
How fast do you think you can get them to move?
我想至少也要几天
It's gonna be at least a couple days.
高盛和摩根斯坦利已经快不行了
Goldman and Morgan Stanley are going down now.
我们今天必须做点什么
We gotta do something today.
比如说?
Like what?
市场不像投行一样 对吗?
The market doesn't like investment banks, right?
所有的商业模型都拿那些钱束手无策
The money's saying "fuck you" to the whole business model.
是的
Yeah.
是的 那让他们变成商业银行
Yeah, so merge them with commercial banks,
把投行变成普通的由联邦政府监管的商业银行
turn them into regular banks regulated by the Fed.
他们就能动用储户的钱了
They can use depositors' cash.
这样他们就能通过贴现窗口
It will give them access to the discount window.
向政府以较低的利率借款
It's cheap government cash.
- 你想让他们变得更大吗?  - 这也是没办法的办法 Hank
- You wanna make them bigger?  - It's a trade-off, Hank.
好处是他们可以逐渐稳定下来
The upside is it'll stabilize them.
坏处是
The downside is,
对的 他们会变得出奇的庞大
yeah, they'll be really fucking big.
去做吧 Tim
Do it, Tim.
快去做
Godspeed.
嗯 给我接Blankfein
Uh, get me Blankfein.
Lloyd 打电话给Vikram Pandit 告诉他你想合并
Lloyd, call Vikram Pandit, talk to him about a merger.
Tim 我们正在尽全力想办法
Tim, we're looking at all our options.
你已经走投无路了 Lloyd 你的银行只能这样做
You don't have options, Lloyd. There's a run on your bank.
你需要钱 花旗又有存款
You need money. Citi has deposits.
花旗现在一团糟 你这里有条不紊 打电话给Pandit
Citi's a mess, you're organized. Call Pandit.
怎么了
Yeah.
我希望你可以考虑考虑和摩根斯坦利合并
I want you to look at merging with Morgan Stanley.
什么 你在开玩笑吧? 我刚刚买了贝尔斯登
What, are you kidding me? I just bought Bear.
我们仍然在想办法让它开始好转
We're still trying to make that work.
你没有买贝尔斯登 它几乎算是送你的
You didn't buy Bear. You got Bear as a Christmas present.
市场现在一团糟 Jamie 跟John Mack聊聊
The market's a fucking disaster, Jamie. Talk to John Mack.
嘿 Geithner说我们可以谈谈合并的事情
Hey, Geithner says we should talk about a merger.
- 你想这样做吗?  - 当然不想
- You wanna do a deal?  - No.
那他为什么要让我打给你?
Then why the fuck did he tell me to call you?
我得到命令去帮助你们公司
I'm under orders to try and help you.
你是个王子 Jamie 真的是王子
You're a prince, Jamie. A real prince.
很显然 有人认为把我们的公司进行合并是一个不错的方法
Apparently, some people seem to think combining our firms would be a good idea.
我想说我对于这通电话受宠若惊
I want you to know I'm flattered by this call.
Vikram 我没有奉承你的意思 相信我
Vikram, I'm not trying to flatter you, believe me.
Geithener打电话来了
Geithner's calling.
一摊子破事
Here comes goddamn eHarmony.
嘿 猜猜看 Jamie一点都不感兴趣
Hey, guess what. Jamie's not interested.
试试Wachovia
Do Wachovia.
他们是闭着眼睛进行抵押贷款买卖的
They were writing mortgages with their eyes closed.
Tim 那只是一块垃圾三明治 忘了他吧
Tim, it's a shit sandwich. Forget it.
我在四小时之内是赶不到你那边的
I haven't been able to reach you for four hours.
这在今天这样的日子里肯定是做不到的
That is totally fucking unacceptable on a day like today.
我不得不让我的公司去评估高盛合并事宜
I had to run my team through the Goldman proposal.
没用的
It's not gonna work.
你已经联系好高盛了 却没给我说一声?
You passed on Goldman without even talking to me?
我不需要在我的资产负债表上多出1兆亿的美元
I don't need another trillion dollars on my balance sheet.
下次我打给你的时候 记得接电话
Next time I call, pick up.
去死吧
Fucker.
问题就在于那些不良资产 我们把他们买过来就好了
The problem is the toxic assets. Let's just buy them.
哦 可以称为现金换垃圾
Ooh. We'll call it Cash for Trash.
当市场稳定下来了 我们再把这些垃圾倾销掉
When the market stabilizes, we'll unload them.
希望是这样 财政部能够把这些钱讨回来
Hopefully, Treasury will get its money back.
- 这是破杯计划的一部分吗?  - 基本上是
- Is that in the Break the Glass plan?  - Basically.
我的这份是不是少了几页 有谁能告诉我余下的几页...
My copy's missing some pages. Could someone else show me the rest of...
这个是简洁版
It's succinct.
我们在国会只有一次机会
We've got one shot with Congress.
你觉得国会会根据这三页纸就签署一份法案吗?
You want them to write a piece of legislation based on three pages?
听着 朋友们
Look, guys,
购买不良资产肯定是一个噩梦
buying toxic assets is gonna be a nightmare.
没人知道这些东西到底值几个子
Nobody knows what the stuff's worth.
也许这些不良资产永远都理不清 银行马上就要倒闭了
It'll take forever to untangle. These banks are going down now.
那我们能怎么做?
So what do we do?
你想要让信用市场继续运作 是吗? 你希望银行能够继续放贷?
You wanna unfreeze credit, right? You want the banks to lend people money?
- 这就是我们想要看到的  - 那就给他们钱让他们放贷
- That's the goal.  - So give them money to lend.
资产注入?
Capital injections?
Dan 摆脱别说傻话
Dan, come on.
我不相信你竟然说出了那个带 "N" 的字眼
I can't believe you're pulling out the "N" word.
我没有说要将银行国有化
I'm not saying nationalize the banks.
我说的是把有问题的银行隔离开 然后进行注资
I'm saying isolate the ones that are really in trouble and make an investment.
- 这做法不是美国人做的  - 当然也不是共和党人做的
- It's un-American.  - It's sure un-Republican.
你让政府变成了一个股东
You'd make the government a stockholder.
什么 我们是不是需要告诉他们怎么去经营 买哪些卖哪些?
What, do we tell them how to manage themselves, what to buy and sell?
像经营邮局一样经营他们? 是那样就太好了
Run them like the post office? 'Cause that works like a dream.
这只是暂时措施 我们可以是没有投票权的股东
We make it temporary. We make ourselves non-voting stockholders.
你不能捧着一叠叠的钞票送到银行里
You can't just hand the banks massive piles of cash.
没人会去理会这些的
Nobody's gonna go for it.
对于共和党来说这是资产国有化 对于民主党来说这就是救助
To the Republicans it's nationalization. To the Democrats it's a bailout.
而且银行会很生气的
And the banks are gonna go ballistic.
抱歉 Dan 这是不可能的 很欣赏你的创造性思维
Sorry, Dan, not gonna happen. Kudos for out-of-the-box thinking.
Neel 如果我们实行你的计划购买那些资产
Neel, if we go with your plan to buy the assets,
我们会花多少钱?
how much is it gonna cost?
那是不可能的
It won't work.
听着 计划只有3页长 而且很空洞
Look, the plan is three pages long, totally vague.
如果购买资产没有用的话 我们会用你的国有化计划 好吗?
If buying the assets doesn't work, we'll nationalize the banks for you, okay?
- 要多少钱?  - 保守估计 需要一万亿
- How much? - To be safe, maybe a trillion.
国会是不会批准一万亿的法案的 永远不会
The Congress will never do a trillion, never.
有11万亿美元的住房抵押债券
There's $11 trillion in residential mortgages.
还有三万亿的商业债券 一共是十四万亿 对吗?
There's three trillion in commercial mortgages. That's 14 trillion, right?
别忘了5%的违约率
You gotta figure about 5% default rate.
14万亿的5%是
5 % of 14 trillion is
七千万美元
$700 billion.
这也比一万亿要好
It's better than a trillion.
让法案通过的唯一方法只能是吓得他们屁滚尿流
The only way to get this done is to just scare them shitless.
这很简单 我自己都吓傻了
That should be easy. I'm scared shitless myself.
2008年9月18日 星期四 雷曼兄弟破产后三天
Barney Frank(马萨诸塞州代表) 众议院金融管理委员会主席
问题资产剥离计划?
Troubled Asset Relief Program?
我们称他为TARP
TARP, we're calling it.
这只是你们的草案?
This is your draft of the bill?
这只是一个修订本 肯定的
Subject to revision, certainly.
Chris Dodd(康乃迪克州代表) 参议院银行委员会主席
我只拿到了三页纸 我是不是漏掉了什么?
I've only got three pages here. Am I missing something?
没有
No.
Richard Shelby(阿拉巴马州代表) 参议院银行委员会副主席
你在着急寻找的只是一张大额的空白支票
You're just looking for a big blank check in a hurry.
这都是为了银行 你也不想
It's all for the banks. You don't want a penny
让布什总统失去他的总统位置
for the average Joe that's about to lose his house?
整件事完全没有任何监管
There's not a scrap of oversight built into this,
钱没有给银行 也没有给你 只是为了解决这个情况
not for the banks or for you, for that matter.
你希望我们简简单单的拿出7000万来相信你?
You want us to simply hand over $700 billion and trust you?
Nancy Pelosi(加利福尼亚州代表) 众议院发言人
你怎么可能没有想到我们的反应?
How is it possible you didn't see this coming?
如果你们想让我再说一遍的话 我没有问题
If you wanna rewind the tape, we can do that.
但是现在 最重要的是我们没时间了
But right now, the one thing we don't have is time.
我们今晚需要一个决议来稳定市场
We need an announcement tonight to calm the market.
我们需要法案在下周通过
We need legislation next week.
我学术研究的内容只有一个
I spent my entire academic career
就是大萧条
studying the Great Depression.
大萧条的起因是因为股票市场的崩盘
The Depression may have started because of a stock market crash,
但是打击到实体经济的是信用体系的瓦解
but what hit the general economy was a disruption of credit,
普通群众无法借钱去做任何事 没法卖房子
average citizens unable to borrow money to do anything, to buy a home,
没法做生意 没法进货
start a business, stock their shelves.
信用是建立现在经济的基础
Credit has the ability to build a modern economy,
但是信用缺乏也可以毁掉经济 迅雷不及掩耳的毁灭
but lack of credit has the power to destroy it, swiftly and absolutely.
如果我们不能做出明确的决断 我们将会重演上世纪30年代的大萧条
If we do not act boldly and immediately, we will replay the Depression of the 1930s,
只是这次情况会更糟 更糟
only this time it will be far, far worse.
如果我们现在不做这些 我们的经济在周一就完了
We don't do this now, we won't have an economy on Monday.
Geithner的电话
Geithner.
我们把议案交到国会了
We took the proposal down to Congress.
他们会通过吗?
Are they gonna go for it?
他们不喜欢那么短的议案
They didn't like the fact that it was short.
我想简单明了可以加分的
I thought concise was a plus.
他们觉得这样太轻薄或者太傲慢或者别的什么
They thought it was flimsy or arrogant or something.
我不知道他们怎么想 但是他们不会通过的
I don't know what they think. They couldn't get past it.
市场已经无法控制了 他们否决这份议案
The market's in a death spiral. They're gonna sink the bill
因为这份议案太短了?
because the proposal is too fucking short?
他们正在研究 他们会把他弄得长一点
They're working on it. They're gonna make it longer,
加入一些其他东西
among other things.
好吧 告诉我你已经有进展了
Look, just tell me you got something.
不 不 我一点进展也没有
No. No, we're nowhere.
还有谁可以帮助摩根斯坦利?
Who's left for Morgan Stanley?
中国投资有限公司
China Investment Corporation.
嗯 或者是三菱集团
Uh, maybe Mitsubishi.
不 日本人是不会做这笔生意的
No, the Japanese will never do this deal.
那高盛有什么进展?
How about Goldman?
高盛找到了联银行 但是他们被拒绝了
Goldman's looking at Wachovia, but they're so fucked,
就连John Mack都不屑一顾
even John Mack turned up his nose.
你必须让议案通过
You gotta get that bill passed.
- 我在努力了  - 那就再努力一点 拜托了
- I'm pushing.  - Well, push harder. Please.
这不会有用的 Hank
This isn't working, Hank.
Hank 怎么了?
Hank?
能让我单独待一会儿吗?
Could you excuse me a moment?
2008年9月21日 雷曼兄弟破产后第六天
哦 我的上帝呀 高先生 高先生
Oh, my God. Gao, Gao.
对于这件事我很抱歉 但是我们无能为力
I am so sorry about this. There's nothing we can do.
这里是纽约 你知道 我们很高兴我们还能在扬基体育馆买一杯啤酒
It's New York, you know. We're lucky we can still buy a beer at Yankee Stadium.
别担心 反正我迟早都会退出的
Don't worry about it. I should quit anyway.
当你准备好了 我们就进去
When you're ready, we'll be inside.
有什么进展吗?
Is there any movement there?
他们给了一个低的离谱的价格 我假装我没听见
They made an extremely low opening offer. I pretended I didn't hear it.
如果摩根斯坦利的问题没有解决 那市场就不能在周一开市
The markets can't open Monday without a resolution of Morgan Stanley.
我们真的很需要你做一个决定
We really need you to do a deal.
- 你打电话给Jamie  - 我打过Jamie了
- You need to call Jamie.  - I called Jamie.
他对我们没兴趣 难度太大了
He doesn't want us. There's too much overlap.
我们已经跟他说过了 他会同意的
We've spoken to him. He'll do it.
为了什么 为了美元? 我为什么要这么做?
For what, a dollar? Why would I do that?
我这里还有中投和三菱集团求着要我呢
I got China Investment and Mitsubishi kicking my tires.
我知道这些家伙 他们不可能及时作出决定的
I know those guys. They're not gonna close a deal in time.
我们希望你打电话给Jamie
We want you to call Jamie.
让我问你个问题
Let me ask you a question.
因为美国国际集团 雷曼和贝尔斯登的事情 已经有3万5千人失业了
35,000 jobs just disappeared in this city between AIG, Lehman and Bear.
如果我们跟Jamie达成协议 他会裁掉2万名摩根斯坦利员工
We make a deal with Jamie, he'll fire 20,000 Morgan Stanley employees.
你觉得这是一个好办法吗?
You think that's good public policy?
John 我们关注的是整个金融体系的安全
John, we are looking at the whole system here.
中国人走了
The Chinese are leaving.
高先生发现我们还在与三菱集团谈判
Gao found out we're also talking to Mitsubishi.
我要走了
I gotta go.
好的 把黑柳找来 再找一个日语翻译
All right, get me Kuroyanagi and a Japanese translator.
今晚 我们跟三菱要签好约
We're closing with Mitsubishi tonight.
Tim Geithner又打电话来了
Tim Geithner's calling again.
你就当没听见
Cover your ears.
你告诉T?im Geithner别来烦我了 我在想办法拯救我的公司
You tell Tim Geithner to fucking blow me. I'm trying to save my company.
2008年9月22日 雷曼兄弟破产后7天
我要和他见面 但是确保约在在午饭之后
Put him on the schedule, but make sure it's after lunch,
因为之前我还要与Madeline碰头 而且...
because that way I can fit Madeline in beforehand. And...
摩根刚才与三菱集团达成交易了
Morgan just made a deal with Mitsubishi.
所以我们是唯一一家没有援助的银行了
So we're the only bank with our dick still in the wind.
我再给巴菲特打个电话
I'm calling Buffett again.
爷爷 他们一直在找你 万一是很重要的事怎么办?
Grandpa, they keep calling. What if it's important?
他们总觉得自己很重要
They always think it's important.
好吧 我会快点解决
All right, I'll make it fast.
巴菲特 感谢你回复我 你最近怎么样?
Warren, thanks for calling back. How are you?
挺好 Lloyd 这次我能帮你做什么?
Just fine, Lloyd. What can I do for you today?
我想跟你谈谈关于入股高盛的事情
I'd like to talk to you about taking a stake in Goldman Sachs.
什么价位? 听上去很贵
What do you have in mind? Sounds expensive.
也许不贵
Maybe not.
你最好给我的是好消息
You better have good news,
也许搞定TRAP之前 我就挂了
because I might be dead before we finish haggling over TARP.
巴菲特准备给高盛注资五十亿
Buffett's throwing five billion into Goldman.
我们脱离险境
We're off the ledge.
暂时而已
For the moment.
十月的惊喜来的早了点
The October surprise arrived a little early,
白宫的总统竞争出现了转机
with a game-changing jolt to the White House race.
是该叫做出奇制胜还是孤注一掷
Call it a master stroke or a desperate Hail Mary pass,
麦凯恩宣布他将暂停竞选
McCain announced he would suspend his campaign
并要求推迟星期五的辩论
and asked for this Friday's debate to be postponed
以便他能回到华盛顿集中精力应对金融危机
so he can return to Washington to focus on the economic crisis.
现在是我们团结一致的时机 再次证明华盛顿有能力
Now is our chance to come together to prove that Washington is once again
领导国家
capable of leading this country.
感谢上帝 他回来了
Thank God he came back.
就像大地英豪里的Daniel Day-Lewis(演员)
Like Daniel Day-Lewis in Last of the Mohicans,
他会拯救我们的!
he will find us!
- 他们要搞砸了  - 发生了什么?
- They're blowing it up.  - What happened?
麦凯恩想趁机介入 挽救局面 但压根不知道怎么下手
McCain wanted to swoop in and save the day, but doesn't have any idea how to do it.
这可是我们认真商量好几天 写了100页的法案
It's a 100-page piece of legislation we've been carefully negotiating for days.
他以为我们就坐着这玩扔纸团?
What, did he think they were gonna sit around and spitball?
是的 当麦凯恩到这
Yeah, when McCain got here
并且发现这事情已经基本解决完了 他就愤怒了
and found out that the deal was basically done, he went apeshit.
共和党没跟上进度 他们想重新来一遍
The Republicans fell in behind their guy. They wanna start all over again.
民主党发飙 共和党想插进来
Democrats flipped out. Republicans dug in.
- 乱七八糟  - 乱七八糟
- Clusterfuck.  - Clusterfuck.
- Hank在哪? - 还在跟麦凯恩说话
- Where's Hank?  - Still talking to McCain.
如果你或者任何其他人做了任何事
If you or anyone else does anything
导致新一轮的大萧条 可别赖在我身上
that causes the next depression, it is not gonna be on me.
我嘴巴很不严的 参议员
I have a big mouth, Senator,
- 口风很松  - 等等
- a very big mouth. - Hold on...
他不是在威胁共和党总统候选人吧?
He's not threatening the Republican presidential nominee, is he?
- 必须采取一些行动  - 不 不 抱歉 离开一下
- Something's gotta be done.  - No, no. Excuse me, please.
民主党的人在哪里?
Where are the Democrats?
他们就在走廊那头
They're right down this way.
- Nancy在吗?  - 是的 她在
- Is Nancy there?  - Yes. Yes, she is.
谢了
Thank you.
Nancy啊...
Nancy...
哦 上帝 Hank 我不知道你还是天主教徒
Oh, Gee, Hank. I didn't know you were Catholic.
我请求你 别毁了这个提案 这次会议很糟糕
I beg of you, don't blow this up. It was a bad meeting,
但是我们必须达成共识
but we need to get together on this.
我们不是想破坏这个提案的一方
We're not the ones trying to blow it up.
我只是请求你能支持我们
I just ask you to stay with us.
拜托了
Please.
参议院在今早9点27分开始讨论援助议案
The House began debating the rescue bill at 9:27 this morning.
约在下午1点28分 国会完成最终投票
At about 1:28 p.m., Congress did finally act.
- 票数非常接近  - 我们马上来看一下
- This is a squeaker of a vote.  - We are down to it right now.
似乎赞成票大多来自民主党
It looks like the Democrats delivered their caucus
而目前来看共和党不大赞同此议案
and the Republicans so far have not.
你认为他们会怎样修改议案
What do you think they could do to change the bill
以便赢得共和党的选票?
to get a few Republican votes over to the other side?
如果他们吊死那些华尔街的首席执行官
If they hang Wall Street CEOs,
我想他们也许能得到更多的选票
I think that would get a few more votes.
我不清楚他们具体能做些什么
I'm not sure what they could do exactly.
国会的领导很可能认为
It is possible that the leadership of the Congress would conclude
没有任何解决方法可以得到多数票的支持
that there's nothing that can get a majority of support
就看Hank Paulson和当局能怎么做了
and see what Hank Paulson can do and the administration can do.
领导们正在协商
Leaders are negotiating right now
谁会拿自己的职位冒险 这就是我所听到的
who risks their seat. And that's what I'm hearing.
如果Pelosi觉得议案不能通过的话
Pelosi wouldn't have brought the bill to the floor
就不会将这个议案提上议程
if she didn't think it would pass.
我不知道结果 Charlie 我没办法回答
I don't know the answer to that, Charlie. I can't answer.
我正在读刚收到的一封邮件
I'm just reading an e-mail that's coming to me.
我想最后的底线就是他们还得重新筹划
I think the bottom line is they gotta go back to the drawing board.
但他们还有时间这么做吗?
Do they have the time, though, to do that?
看看道琼斯工业平均指数
Look at the Dow Jones Industrial Average.
知道吗 你们将会迎来一个大甩卖
You know you're gonna get a sell-off.
你们 此时此刻 我们只能抓紧救生筏
You guys, at this point, we just gotta hold on to the sides of the kayak
挺过去 因为
and ride through this because...
他们没通过议案
They didn't pass it.
- 他们没通过议案  - 这还不够
- They did not pass it.  - It just wasn't enough.
议案以九票之差 未能获得通过 Bill
They're gonna end up being nine votes short, Bill.
再说一次 Steve
Say that again, Steve.
我认为他们会以九票之差否决这个议案...
I think they're gonna end up being nine votes...
如果他们得到剩下的六票... 还有五票尚未投出
If they get all six... Five of the remaining votes,
现在他们差10票 剩下的五票都支持议案
they'll be 10 votes short now, if they get all five remaining.
票选结果在墙上
The writing is on the wall there.
我们却失望的坐在地板上
And we're here down on the floor.
当然 交易员已经站在那
Of course, traders have been standing around.
看着 我们都三五成群的站着...
Look, we're all here in knots...
媒体在新闻发布室等你
The networks are waiting for you in the press room.
我甚至无法
I can't even...
我们得重头再来
We have to go back again.
他们不能对新议案说不
They don't get to say no on this.
好的
Okay.
白宫方面想跟你会面
The White House wants a meeting.
很好 我们要带着新策略去
Good. We'll come up with a new strategy.
白宫必须给国会施压
The White House has to push harder on the Hill.
同时 我们要想好如何运作资金
Meanwhile, we need to keep working on what we do with the money.
让我们表现的好像议案能通过一样
Let's act like this is gonna work.
这种情况下 我们还是谈谈资本注入吧
In that case, let's talk about cash injections.
- 又来了  - 我们不能把银行国有化
- Here we go again.  - We can't nationalize the banks.
这不是国有化
It's not nationalizing...
这就是为什么日本经济衰退达十年的原因
That's how Japan got itself a decade-long recession.
那就是我们想要的结果吗?
Is that where we wanna go?
我们还有什么别的选择?
What else do we have?
现金换垃圾
Cash for Trash.
购入不良资产依旧是我们的出路
Buying toxic assets is still our go-to move.
好吧 想办法简化方案
All right. Find a way to simplify it.
Dan 做个方案出来
Dan, work something up.
让我们看看会是什么情况 讨论一下
For discussion purposes, let's see what it would look like.
针对那些支持7千亿华尔街援助的人而言
For those who supported the $700 billion Wall Street bailout,
这是一次出乎意料的失败
it was a surprising and stunning failure
当众议院投票否决此议案时
when the House of Representatives voted to reject it.
对总统布什而言 被共和党同僚打击
It's a stinging defeat for President Bush,
是一次惨痛的失败
delivered at the hands of his fellow Republicans.
我们提出一个宏大的计划是因为我们面临着严重的问题
We put forth a plan that was big because we've got a big problem.
现实就是我们处在非常紧急的情况下
The reality is that we're in an urgent situation.
并且后果会日益恶化
And the consequences will grow worse each day
如果我们不采取行动
if we do not act.
两天后
- 我明白 我一直都在说  - 起草新议案
- I know. I keep telling...  - Draft of the new bill.
他们那边有什么进展了吗?
Are they having any luck with it?
白宫认为先向参议院施加压力
The White House thinks they got a better shot of pushing it
效果会更好 希望他们是对的
through the Senate side first. Hopefully they're right.
他们叫我们收手 交给他们处理
They asked us to back off and let them handle it.
所以我在试着收手
So I'm trying to back off.
购买不良资产还是行不通
Buying toxic assets isn't gonna work.
- 为什么行不通?  - 太慢了
- Why not?  - It's too slow.
我想我之前就说过
I think I've been saying that.
好吧 我们知道这会很复杂 但是有多慢
Well, we knew it was complicated, but how slow...
两个月 也许更多
Two months, maybe more.
我们怎么会不知道...
How is it possible we didn't know how...
我没问会要多久 行不?
I didn't ask how long it would take, okay?
有别的建议吗?
Can we move on?
那么也许我们能谈谈资本注入
So maybe we can talk about capital injections.
Dan 我们真不能那么做
Dan, we really can't.
我想我们没选择了
I think we're gonna have to.
就算Neel能加快进程 实际上不大可能
Even if Neel could expedite the process, which seems unlikely,
体系正在崩溃 银行现在就需要钱
the system is crumbling. The banks need money now.
如果注资是稳定整个体系最有效的方式
If cash injections are the most efficient way to stabilize them,
那么我们就不能
then we can't back off
因为我们不愿意成为是要将几家银行变成国有化的人而退却
because we're uncomfortable being the men who nationalized a few American banks.
可以肯定的是 这更快
It's faster, that's for sure.
这能够把我们从险境中拉出来 是的 激活整个系统
It will push us back off the precipice, yes, unfreeze the system.
我们给他们一些钱然后他们贷出去
We give them some money and they lend it out.
议案通过
The motion is adopted.
在否决布什政府的TARP计划之后
After rejecting the Bush Administration's TARP plan
仅过了四天 众议院今日通过了议案
only four days ago, the House passed it today.
现在最大的问题是 投资者是否能从此消息中得到慰藉
The big question now, whether investors will take comfort in the news.
市场指数显示股票仍在大幅下跌
Current indicators show the stock market is continuing its free fall.
喂?
Hello?
巴菲特 我是Hank
Warren, it's Hank.
抱歉 这么晚了
I'm sorry. It's late.
我吵醒你了吗?
Am I waking you?
没 没有
No, not at all.
能帮我出出主意吗?
Can I pick your brain for a minute?
当然 什么情况?
Sure. What's the problem?
怎么样让一家健全的的银行接受资本注入?
How do you get a healthy bank to accept a capital injection?
我不得不大老远从加利福尼亚跑过来
I had to drag my ass all the way here from California.
他们甚至不告诉我为什么要过来
They wouldn't even tell me why.
没人知道这是要干什么吗?
Nobody knows what this is about?
不知道
Nope.
跟Jamie谈过了?
Talk to Jamie?
恩 他会没事的
Yep. He'll be fine.
你告诉他接下来要发生什么了吗?
Did you tell him what was coming?
额 我告诉他我们会迫使他接受
Uh, did I tell him we're about to make him swallow
不需要的注资了吗? 没说
a capital injection he doesn't need? No.
我只告诉他 我们需要他的帮助
I, uh... I told him we need his help
并且我非常礼貌的请求他今天不要跟我们作对
and I asked him very politely not to fuck with us today.
他明白了
He got it.
她在这了
She's here.
Sheila Bair 美国联邦存款保险公司主席
绅士们 这能奏效吗?
Gentlemen. We think this is gonna work?
啊 是的 他们会喜欢的
Oh, yeah. They're gonna love it.
我们现在要着眼于美国的实际需求
We are of the view that the United States needs
要采取坚决有力的行动
to take strong, decisive action
以缓解金融体系的压力
to arrest the stress in our financial system.
通过新授权的TARP方案
Through our new TARP authority,
财政部将向这间房间里
Treasury will purchase preferred stock
与会的每家银行 购买优先股
in each of the banks represented in this room.
头五年 年收益为5%
That stock will yield 5 % the first five years,
其后为9%
9 % after that.
我们给你钱 你们借出去
We give you money. You lend it out.
这可以激活信贷 稳定银行 重建信心
It will unfreeze credit, stabilize the banks, restore confidence.
每个人都会因为体系中更多的资金而获益
Everyone will be better off with more capital in the system.
这就是为什么你们九个人
And that is why all nine of you
都要参与这个计划
will participate in the program.
我们中有些人不需要资金
Some of us don't need any capital.
你们都需要
You all need capital.
你们不知道在未来一年里市场会变成什么样
You have no idea what the market's gonna look like in a year.
你也不知道
Neither do you.
我可不是你们这些鼓弄新花样的纽约佬
I'm not one of you New York guys with your fancy products.
为什么我要呆在这房间里商量救助你们?
Why am I in this room talking about bailing you out?
强势银行将为弱势银行买单
The stronger banks will serve as cover for the weaker banks.
如果只有部分银行接受注资 那将成为一种信号
If just some of you take it, the money's a signal
就是 这家银行无法存活 市场将吞噬掉它
that a bank is too weak to survive. The market will devour it.
我们讨论的金额是多少?
How much are we talking about?
1250亿
A hundred and twenty-five billion.
美国银行 150亿
Bank of America, 15 billion.
纽约梅隆银行 30亿
Bank of New York Mellon, three billion.
花旗集团 250亿
Citigroup, 25 billion.
高盛 100亿
Goldman Sachs, 10 billion.
摩根大通 250亿
JPMorgan, 25 billion.
美林证 100亿
Merrill Lynch, 10 billion.
摩根斯坦利 100亿
Morgan Stanley, 10 billion.
道富银行 20亿
State Street, two billion.
富国银行 250亿
Wells Fargo, 25 billion.
购买不良资产的那个方案怎么了?
What happened to buying toxic assets?
- 那不是个好主意吗?  - 那样太慢了
- Wasn't that the idea?  - It's too slow.
在这之前体系就会崩溃
It'll be dead before we sort it out.
所以 我们就这么把缰绳交给你了?
So, we're just handing the reins over to you?
这笔交易实际上很不错了
The deal's actually pretty good.
你现在对此不屑一顾 等到我们还是得来援助你的时候
You turn your nose up at this now and we have to rescue you later,
条件可就不这么有吸引力了
the terms won't be nearly as attractive.
这是很便宜的资本 这不是最差的注意
It's cheap capital. It's not the worst idea in the world.
这是针对我们中间那些已经有足够资本的
It is for those of us who already have capital.
我们将成为没投票权的股东 这只是暂时的举措
We will be non-voting shareholders. This will be a temporary measure.
要是我们拒绝参与呢?
What if we decline to be involved?
美国联邦存款保险公司的主席就坐在这里
The Chairman of the FDIC is sitting right there.
明天你就会发现
Tomorrow you'll find out
你并不像你想的那样拥有雄厚资本
that you're not as well capitalized as you think you are.
你们会采取什么样的保障措施
What kind of protections can you offer on changes
针对补偿措施的改变?
for compensation policy?
我的意思是 如果政府要成为共有者
I mean, if the government is going to become a part-owner,
是不是表明将由政府来指定酬金?
does that mean that the government is going to dictate compensation?
此刻你是在问我有关你的奖金问题吗 John?
Are you asking me about your bonus right now, John?
我在经营一家公司
I'm running a company.
如果美联储告诉我 我不能向有才能的人提供有竞争力的薪酬
If the Fed tells me I can't offer competitive pay for talent,
你将导致这个国家有史以来最严重的人才流失
you're gonna launch the biggest brain drain this country's ever seen.
这就是你们要经营银行的方式?
Is that the way you wanna run the banks?
在偿还欠款给财政部之前
Until the money is repaid to the Treasury,
会有一些限制扣税和黄金降落伞(公司控制权变动需要给高管进行补偿的协定)的规定
there will be some limitations on tax deductions and golden parachutes.
- 果然  - 我真不明白
- Well, there you go.  - I don't really understand
为什么讨论这个话题还如此严肃
why there needs to be so much tension about this.
这个国家在面临自从大萧条以来最严重的经济危机
The country is facing the worst economy since the Great Depression.
如果金融体系崩溃 你们每个人都会遭殃
If the financial system collapses, it will take every one of you down.
给我文件
Give me the papers.
- 你不能就这么签了  - 哦 为什么不行?
- You can't just sign it.  - Oh, no?
- 没有你的董事会的同意  - 我的董事会24小时都待命
- Not without your board. - My board's on 24-hour notice.
我想他们会同意的
I think they'll go along with it.
如果他们不同意 那就炒了我
And if they don't, they'll fire me.
其他人呢?
Anyone else?
他们打算签吗?
Are they gonna do it?
他们要联系各自的董事会
They're calling their boards.
- 那是个好信号  - 如果他们同意
- That's a good sign.  - If they do go along with this,
我们需要在宣布注资的同时 公布其他举措
we should announce something alongside the injections, uh,
也许是一个收购房屋贷款抵押的计划
maybe a program to buy up mortgages.
我不想草率的公布些不成熟的计划
I'm not rushing out some half-assed plan
只是为了显示我们做了什么
just to make it look like we're doing something.
或许我们能补充些限制条件 限制这些钱的用途
Maybe we just beef up the restrictions on how they spend the money,
以去除毒瘤
something to take the stink off.
加更多的条件的话 他们就不会答应了
Put more restrictions on it, they won't take it.
今天完成的事情太多了
One thing too many for today.
我们所知道的是他们差点搞垮了全美国的经济
They almost bring down the US economy as we know it,
但是我们却不能限制他们如何使用
but we can't put restrictions on how they spend
我们给他们的1250亿美元
the $125 billion we're giving them
就因为他们可能不会接受
because they might not take it.
这是什么?
What's this?
那是 额
That is, um,
一种有毒镖蛙
a poison dart frog.
Wendy在圭亚那照的
Wendy took it in Guyana.
这是你的吗?
Is this yours?
Al Capone(美国黑帮教父)的
Al Capone's.
九家银行中的八个已经同意了
Eight out of nine are in.
- 美国银行还在等他的董事会 但是...  - 他也会同意的
- B of A is still waiting on its board, but...  - It's gonna go through.
我要给众议院办公室打电话
I'll call the Speaker's office.
还有 我们安排你跟总统电话联系下
And, uh, we're gonna get you on the phone with the President.
好的
Okay.
就因为我们的商议 道琼斯指数涨了900点
Dow is up 900 points just because we were meeting.
太好了
Well, that's good.
That's good.
这样做是对的
It was the right thing.
绝对的
Absolutely.
我原本准备好应对更强的反对
I was prepared for more blowback.
他们没有选择了 他们明白这点
They didn't have a choice. They knew that.
好吧 我当然希望他们
Well, I certainly hope that they...
什么?
What?
我希望他们会把钱用在我们要求的地方
I hope they use the money the way we're asking them to.
他们会贷出去 是吧?
They will lend it out, won't they?
他们一定会的
Of course they will.
虽然TRAP得到通过 但是几家银行仍未进行贷款 市场继续动荡
失业率超过10% 数百万的家庭因丧失抵押品赎回权而无家可归
2009年 动荡的市场逐渐稳定 国际金融形势的恶化得到缓解
最大的几家银行已经赎回了TRAP中政府购买的优先股
2010年 对华尔街的补偿已经达到1350亿美元的新纪录
10家银行的资产占拥有全美银行资产总数的77%
他们被称为 大而不倒
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hd.cnscg.com/==--
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
协调：潇妹纸
翻译：Flower一休 千欲 蓝岸 wendychen11 13711 Kim
校对：微微